<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The light and dark sides of God or A plain and brief discourse of the light side (God, Heaven and angels.) The dark side (Devill, sin, and Hell.) As also of the Resurrection and Scripture. : All which are set forth in their severall natures and beings, according to the spirituality of the Scripture. / Written by Jacob Bauthumley.</title>
            <author>Bauthumley, Jacob.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1165B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16169</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11732526</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11732526</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171557</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76129)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171557)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 11:7 or 2561:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The light and dark sides of God or A plain and brief discourse of the light side (God, Heaven and angels.) The dark side (Devill, sin, and Hell.) As also of the Resurrection and Scripture. : All which are set forth in their severall natures and beings, according to the spirituality of the Scripture. / Written by Jacob Bauthumley.</title>
                  <author>Bauthumley, Jacob.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Learner at the Black-more in Bishopsgate-streete.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P. 83 numbered "43."</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing B1169 at reel 11:7 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.) and as Wing (2nd ed.) B1165B at reel 2561:15.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
               <term>Resurrection.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171557:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171557:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Light and Dark ſides of GOD Or a plain and brief DISCOURSE, OF The light ſide <hi>God, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> and <hi>Angels.</hi> The dark ſide <hi>Devill, Sin,</hi> and <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo of the Reſurrection</hi> and <hi>Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which are ſet forth in their Severall Natures and Beings, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſpirituality of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Jacob Bauthumley.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>I thank thee O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them to Babes, even ſo it is thy pleaſure.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>The ſpirituall man judgeth all things, and he himſelf is judged of none.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>William Learner</hi> at the <hi>Black-more</hi> in <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreete.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171557:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171557:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171557:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171557:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:171557:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171557:4"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have onely directed my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to thee, though I know the moſt unto whoſe hand it may come cannot read it; But that it will be a <hi>Barbarian</hi> to them, and they to It. However, if I be beſide them; yet I am not beſide my ſelfe. (If I be it is to God) The reaſon why I have not
<pb facs="tcp:171557:5"/>directed it to any particular man, or ſort of men what ever: as is uſuall in things of this nature, is, becauſe I deſire not any mans approbation of it, as knowing I am not ſubject to mans judgement: neither would I have any man to ſubject himſelf to mine: neither ſhall I be aſhamed to own what I have writ for the preſent, or to caſt it away for the future, if God ſhall lead me thereunto. I have caſt up my accounts what all will amount unto, upon either of the former conſiderations, and ſo have ſweet peace in my ſpirit, in my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thoughts and apprehenſions, leaving the iſſue of all to the wiſe diſpoſing providence. All I deſire is, that thoſe to whom theſe few lines may come, would (if they can) be ſo charitable of me, as to conceive and judge, that I have not writ any thing with any ſpirit of oppoſition to any ſort of men, under what forme of godlineſſe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as knowing, that there is a ſweet appearance of God in them All. And however my perſon, and parts be meane in the Worlds Eye, and ſo may caſt an <hi>odium</hi> upon the things that I hold forth; yet I ſhall runne the hazard in that kinde, and leave the Lord to gaine his own Honour and Glory in it; as ſeeing by ſweet experience, it is one of his greateſt deſignes in the World, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the high and mighty things thereof, by the
<pb facs="tcp:171557:5"/>moſt mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and contemptible; And ſo though men be not ſatisfied, yet herein I ſhall receive ſweet content in my own ſpirit, that my worke ſhall either burne and conſume, or elſe abide the fiery tryall of mens indignation; And as I ſhall wiſh no man to embrace it, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne me: So I ſhall neither thank them that do the one, or condemne them that do the other.</p>
            <p>For the ſubject matter of the Diſcourſe, I muſt confeſſe they are things of that nature, that are not obvious to every capacity, and ſo lye obnoxious unto their cenſure; and when time was, I ſhould have been as ready to have ſat in Judgement againſt the Maintainer of ſuch Principles; yet to me they are ſuch as wherein the Myſtery of godlyneſſe mainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, and ſo are not to be ſlighted.</p>
            <p>And however, I do not looke that I, or any man elſe ſhall receive much by this, or any other Booke; which had almoſt perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me, to have been ſilent in this kind; yet was I inwardly enforced thereunto, to eaſe the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that lay upon my ſpirit; which was one great motive to me, to act my part ſo publickly.</p>
            <p>Beſides, having converſt with men under ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall formes and adminiſtrations, not to ſpeake of thoſe of the inferiour ſort, as <hi>Papiſts,
<pb facs="tcp:171557:6"/>Epiſcoparians</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> But thoſe that are got to the higheſt: as <hi>Independents</hi> an a <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> commonly ſo called; and ſeriouſly viewing the carnall apprehention of things in themſelves, and there miſ-appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of the minde of God held forth by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, condemning them as Heriticall and Blaſphemous, in whom the Myſteryes of the Kingdome are moſt clearly revealed, and they themſelves placeing Religion, and the Myſtery of godlineſſe in outward Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and adminiſtrations of which they are all but Shaddowes; Having a ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite of a Creature happyneſſe, and ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment; and ſo are acted to attaine to the End. In all theſe reſpects, I could not but gratifie them ſo farre, as to ſet forth what is held out by a certaine Generation of Men and Woemen in the World; That if it may be, there may be ſuch a favourable opinion of us from them, that we neither deny there is a GOD, <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Hell, Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>Scripture,</hi> as the World is made to believe we do; And I thinke they are all as plainly, and briefly made out, as they themſelves could deſire.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171557:6"/>
            <p> And further, I know by experience, that there are ſome with whom my ſpirit ſweetly cloſed in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity thereof, and that travell with me in the ſame birth; yet are not able to bring forth their conceptions, for ſo much as many times, the Truth ſuffers by a weake delivery; and for their ſakes have I held this Glaſſe before them, that ſo they may be the better able to deſcribe themſelves to others; and to help them to bring forth that out of their mouths, which perhaps may lye in the bottome of their hearts.</p>
            <p>For theſe Reaſons have I taken the boldneſſe to ſet pen to Paper, though otherwiſe I was unwilling, deſiring that, and no more of others then what I would do to them; which is, to let every man ſtand and fall to his own Maſter.</p>
            <p>One thing I thought fit to premiſe, onely to ſatisfie any that ſhall be ſo weake, as to make it a matter of offence to them. In that I have not ſet downe the chapter and verſe, of many places of Scripture, which I do hint upon all along the Diſcourſe. To anſwer them, and ſo to ſalve up that pretended ſoare; I found things of ſuch a Myſterious
<pb facs="tcp:171557:7"/>nature as they are, that while I was looking for them in the Letter of the Scripture, I was at a great loſſe, in the preſent delivery of my ſelfe, of thoſe things which I found ſpiritually and ſecretly conveyed to me in the Spirit; and ſo rather then I would looſe, or let paſſe what was ſpiritually diſcovered in me, I was willing to omit the outward viewing of them in a chapter or verſe. Beſides, there is nothing laide downe by me by way of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or formall diſpute, which might ingage me to an outward proofe of things, as men u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually do in matters of controverſie; and what is poſitively affirmed, there is punctually Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for. But my deſigne was mainly, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver my private Meditations, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of ſuch things which are moſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally conceived of. I thought it not therefore neceſſary, to trouble my ſelf or the Reader, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h multiplicity of places of Scripture, to prove thoſe things of which I hed ſo reall and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall a Teſtimony of in my own ſpirit; and which I am confident, that the moſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall man can ſet his ſeale unto. And yet I dare affirme to the moſt rigid ſpirit that
<pb facs="tcp:171557:7"/>workes in any man at this day againſt the things aſserted, That there is not any thing poſitively affirmed; but I could with more eaſe prove the truth of them, by divers Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Scripture and reaſon, then he could with any truth or Scripture oppoſe them; and any man that ſhall impartially weigh things, may ſee that there is nothing in the Treatiſe then the very Language, and correſpondency of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the Letter of it: will eaſily ſpeake, and ſweetly comply with: in a ſpirituall ſence. So much I thought good to premiſe by way of <hi>Preface</hi> to the <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi> All that GOD aimes at in ſuch things as are of this nature, is but to make out his owne Honour and Glory before men, and to gaine eſteeme from them; And all I aime at, is, that we might reſolve all the Comforts, Glory, and future felicity into GOD againe; and ſo to make GOD All, and the Creature nothing, and if in the <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> I ſhall detract or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicate from either of the Ends, I am much miſtaken, and ſhall willingly confeſſe with that Prophet, <hi>O Lord thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived me, and I was deceived.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171557:8"/>
            <p> And ſo I leave the Diſcourſe, and thee together; and if you happyly agree, it is all the fruire of my labour that I expect to Reape; If not, I ſhall willingly waite an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to make you both Friends,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>As I am to every man.</hi> J. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171557:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Light and dark ſides OF GOD.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God, what ſhall I ſay thou art, when thou canſt not be named? what ſhall I ſpeak of thee, when in ſpeaking of thee, I ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but contradiction? For if I ſay I ſee thee, it is nothing but thy ſeeing of thy ſelfe; for there is nothing in me capable of ſeeing thee but thy ſelf: If I ſay I know
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171557:9"/>thee, that is no other but the know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy ſelf; for I am rather known of thee, then know thee: If I ſay I love thee, it is nothing ſo, for there is nothing in me can love thee but thy ſelf; and therefore thou doſt but love thy ſelf: My ſeeking of thee is no other but thy ſeeking of thy ſelfe: My delighting en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying thee, is no other but thy delighting in thy ſelfe, and enjoying of thy ſelfe after a moſt unconceivable manner.</p>
               <p>If I ſay I prayſe thee, bleſſe or magnifie thee; it is no other but thy prayſing, bleſſing, and magnifying of thy ſelf.</p>
               <p>I ſay thou art infinite, but what that is I cannot tell, becauſe I am finite. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am led to believe, that whatſoever thy Scripture or any man elſe ſpeaks of thee, it is but thy meer condeſcention to ſpeak to us in the language of men, and ſo we ſpeak of thee to one another.</p>
               <p>For this I know, that whatſoever the Scripture or any man elſe ſpeakes what thou art, I know thou art not that, becauſe no man can ſay what thou art. And therefore when the Scripture ſaith thou art a ſpirit: It is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a ſpirit is the higheſt thing or tearme that men can give or apprehend: For thou art beyond any expreſſion, and therefore thou
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171557:9"/>art pleaſed to cloathe thy ſelf with ſuch Titles and Expreſſions of ſpirit, love, mercy, power, ſtrength, or whatſoever is amiable or high in eſteeme among men, to honour thy ſelf, and beget an high eſteeme and lawfull reſpect of thy ſelf from men.</p>
               <p>And therefore whatſoever I ſpeak or write of thee, it is from thy writing and ſpeaking in me; for I really ſee, that thou doſt not ſpeek to men, but in men; becauſe there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in man capable of thy ſpeaking or hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but thy ſelf, onely this man declares out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly what he hath heard and ſeen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and yet that outward Declaration is of God alſo; for thou being the life and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all Creatures, they ſpeak and move, yea live in thee; and whatever any Creature is, it is that as it is in thee: And therefore thou art pleaſed to give thy ſelf that Title, <hi>I Am.</hi> This therefore I can ſay of thee, That thou onely art, and there is none beſide thee: But what thou art I cannot tell. Onely this I ſee, that there is nothing hath a Being, but thy Being is in it, and it is thy Being in it that gives it a Being: and ſo I am ready to ſay with thy Servant: Lord whither ſhall I go from thy preſence? for it is thy preſence and Being, that is the ſubſiſtance and Being of all Creatures and things, and fills Heaven and Earth and all other places.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171557:10"/>
               <p> And therefore I cannot as I have carnally conceived, and as men generally do, that God hath his perſonall being, and preſence in one place more then another, or that he hath a ſimple, pure, glorious, and intire being circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed or confined in a place above the Starres and Firmament, which the men of the World call Heaven: And that all Creatures here below, are the products of that Being, and had their Being of him, and yet diſtinct from him: But the ſpirit in me ſpeakes other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and ſaith, I muſt not aſcend up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to fetch Chriſt thence, nor deſcend into the depth to fetch him from thence; for the Word is even in you, which Word is God, and God is the Word.</p>
               <p>Nay, I ſee that God is in all Creatures, Man and Beaſt, Fiſh and Fowle, and every green thing, from the higheſt Cedar to the Ivey on the wall; and that God is the life and being of them all, and that God doth really dwell, and if you will perſonally; if he may admit ſo low an expreſſion in them all, and hath his Being no where elſe out of the Creatures.</p>
               <p>Further, I ſee that all the Beings in the World are but that our Being, and ſo he may well be ſaid, to be every where as he is, and ſo I cannot exclude him from Man or Beaſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171557:10"/>or any other Creature: Every Creature and thing having that Being living in it, and there is no difference betwixt Man and Beaſt; but as Man carries a more lively Image of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Being then any other Creature: For I ſee the Power, Wiſdom, and Glory of God in one, as well as another, onely in that Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture called Man, God appeares more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in then the reſt.</p>
               <p>And truly, I find by experience, the grand reaſon why I have, and many others do now uſe ſet times of prayer, and run to formall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and other outward and low ſervices of God: the reaſon hath been, and is, becauſe men look upon a God, as being without them, and remote from them at a great diſtance, as if he were locally in Heaven, and ſitting there onely, and would not let down any bleſſing or good things, but by ſuch and ſuch a way and meanes.</p>
               <p>But Lord, how carnall was I thus to fancie thee? Nay I am confident, that there is never a man under the Sun that lookes upon God in ſuch a forme; but muſt be a groſſe Idolator, and fancie ſome corporall ſhape of him, though they may call it ſpiritual.</p>
               <p>Did men ſee that that God was in them, and framing all their thoughts, and working all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171557:11"/>their works, and that he was with them in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> conditions: what carnall ſpirit would reach out to that by an outward way, which ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually is in him, and which he ſtands really poſſeſt of? and which divine wiſdom ſees the beſt, and that things can be no otherwiſe with him. I ſhall ſpeak my own experience herein, that I have made God mutable as my ſelf, and therefore as things and conditions have changed, I thought that God was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry or pleaſed, and to have faln a humbling my ſelf; or otherwiſe in thankfulneſs, never looking or conſidering that God is one intire perfect and immutable Being, and that all things were according to the Councel of his own will, and did ſerve the deſigne of his own glory: but thought that my ſins or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walking did cauſe him to alter his purpoſe of good or evill to me.</p>
               <p>But now I cannot looke upon any condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or action, but methinks there appears a ſweet concurrance of the ſupreame will in it nothing comes ſhort of it, or goes beyond it, nor any man ſhall doe or be any thing, but what ſhall fall in a ſweet compliance with it; It being the wombe wherein all things are conceived, and in which all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were formed and brought fourth.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171557:11"/>
               <p> Yea further, there is not the leaſt Flower or Herbe in the Field but there is the Divine being by which it is, that which it is; and as that that departs out of it, ſo it comes to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and ſo it is to day clothed by God, &amp; to morow caſt into the Oven: when God ceaſes to live in it then it comes to nothing, and ſo all the viſible Creatures are lively re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances of the Divine being. But if this be ſo, ſome may ſay: Then look how many Creatures there are in the world, there is ſo many Gods, and when they dye and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, then muſt God alſo die with them, which can be no leſſe then blaſphemy to affirm.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, and it is apparent to me, that all the Creatures in the world; they are not ſo many diſtinct Beings, but they are but one intire Being, though they be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in reſpect of their formes; yet their Being is but one and the ſame Being, made out in ſo many formes of fleſh, as Men and Beaſt, Fiſh and Fowle, Trees and Herbes: For though theſe two laſt Trees and Herbes have not the life ſo ſenſibly or lively; yet it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain there is a Life and Being in them, by which they grow to that maturity and perfection, that they become ſerviceable for the uſe of Man, as other Creatures are; and yet I muſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171557:12"/>not exclude God from them; for as God is pleaſed to dwel in fleſh, and to dwel with and in man, yet is he not fleſh, nor doth the fleſh partake of the divine Being. Onely this, God is pleaſed to live in fleſh, and as the Scripture ſaith, he is made fleſh, and he appeares in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall formes of fleſh, in the forme of Man and Beaſt, and other Creatures, and when theſe have performed the deſigne and will of God, that then as the fleſh of Man and other Creatures, came from the Earth, and are not capable of knowing God, or partaking of the divine nature, and God ceaſing to live in them, and being gone out of them, that then they all ſhall return to their firſt principle of duſt, and God ſhall as he did from all eternity, live in himſelf, before there was a World or Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: ſo he ſhall to all eternity live and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy himſelf in himſelf, in ſuch a way as no man can utter: and ſo I ſee him yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever: The <hi>Alpha</hi> and the <hi>Omega,</hi> the beginning and end of all things.</p>
               <p>Yea further, as God ſhall ceaſe to live in fleſh, and ſo all things ſhall come to nothing that are below him: Then ſhall he live in ſpirit, he will ceaſe to live in the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and live is the divine, and ſo he is that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171557:12"/>eternall and everlaſting life, in whom all the glory, beauty and excellency of Creatures are wrapt up; for as all things were let out of God: ſo ſhall they all give up their Being, life and happineſs into God again; and ſo we may ſay truly, that God or the divine Being never dies; though the Clothing diſſolve, and come to nothing, yet the inward man ſtill lives; though the ſhadow dies, yet the ſoule or ſubſtance which is God, lives to all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Further, to me it is cleare, that there is nothing that partakes of the divine nature, or is of God, but it is God. The reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are no diſtinctions in God, he Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one individed eſſence: however Man out of a ſimple ignorance, diſtinguiſh of his Will, and of his love, of his juſtice and mercy, of common guifts, and of ſpirituall, as they call them; yet I cannot ſee any ſuch things in God, or that he is capable of any degrees of more or leſſe, or that he loves one man more then another, or hates one man more then another. However the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Jacob</hi> have I loved, and <hi>Eſau</hi> have I hated; it is but after the manner of men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for I cannot ſee that there is love or hatred in God, or any ſuch paſſions: that which admits of degrees is not perfect.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:171557:13"/>
               <p> Indeed in reſpect of men as they imagine God is angry and he is pleaſed, he threatens and he promiſes, he Commands and he puniſhes; but in God there is no ſuch things, he being that <hi>I Am,</hi> which changes not; but all things are according to the Councel of his own will: And God loves the Being of all Creatures, yea, all men are alike to him, and have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived lively impreſſions of the divine nature, though they be not ſo gloriouſly and purely manifeſted in ſome as in others, ſome live in the light ſide of God, and ſome in the dark ſide; But in reſpect of God, light and darkneſs are all one to him; for there is nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God, but onely to our apprehenſion. And for the proud ſelfiſh Being which is the <hi>Eſau,</hi> is contrary to the ſincere and pure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Being, which is the <hi>Jacob:</hi> But the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of both ſerve the deſigne of God as we ſhall in the ſequell of the diſcourſe ſhew. But to ſpeak a little more of the preſent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect; I wonder how that Divinity came into the world, and which is ſtill maintained and uſed by thoſe that call them ſelves Divines; who doe ſtill hould and teach others, that there are three perſons in the God-head, and yet but one God.</p>
               <p>Surely it is a myſtery to mee; But I rather
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171557:13"/>thinke it is a myſtery of Iniquity, for I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a perſon cannot be without an eſſence, ſo that it plainly appeares there muſt be three eſſences in God, and yet theſe three muſt be but one; But I ſuppoſe the moſt of them have received ſo much new Light that they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of ſuch a Tenent, there being nothing in Scripture or reaſon to countenance ſuch a groſſe and carnall conceit of God: But I ſhall not enter upon any thing controvertall: one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I ſhall give you what is made out in me, and I conceive no other what the Scripture holds out in the letter, and ſo it is true, that there are three that bear record in Heaven, and yet theſe three but one. He doth not ſpeak three perſons, but three, and that thus, as farre as I conceive: The Father is God from all eternity, who's Being was in himſelf, having all Beings wrapt up in himſelf; This God letting himſelf and his Being in ſeverall formes of fleſh is God the Son: For I do not apprehend that God was onely manifeſt in the fleſh of Chriſt, or the man called Chriſt; but that he as really and ſubſtantially dwells in the fleſh of other men and Creatures, as well as in the man Chriſt, though as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſpeaks, he was the moſt expreſs Image,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171557:14"/>and that the fulneſſe of the God-head dwelt bodily in him; that is, in reſpect of manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but otherwiſe I conceive that God who cannot admit of degrees, can be ſaid to dwell in him more then another, and I might ſhew that his Being in ſpirit, is much more glorious then his Being in fleſh; the one being but a ſhadow and Type of the other.</p>
               <p>But I forbear, becauſe it may afford ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe of it ſelf, and returne to what we have in hand; and that is, that God the Sonne is God manifeſt in fleſh: Now that we call Holy Ghoſt, is God living in Spirit, and all theſe are not three diſtinct Beings, onely one Being made out in three ſeverall tearmes. To make it a little plainer, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith; <hi>God is Love;</hi> and yet it tells us of a threefold Love: The firſt is Gods Love to us, the ſecond is our Love to God, the third is our Love to one another.</p>
               <p>Now it is plaine, theſe are not three, but one: For by the ſame Love that God loves us, by the ſame Love we love him; we love him, becauſe he loves us, and it is the ſame Love by which we love one another; and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>He that loves not his brother, loves not God:</hi> And ſo we have communion with God, when we have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171557:14"/>with one another: So that Gods Love to us, and our Love to him, and to one another; are not three loves but one: ſo in like manner: Love is the Father; this Love manifeſted in Fleſh is the Sonne; this Love loving the loved, is the Holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one.</p>
               <p>The Father is God forming all things; the Son is God, who is formed and manifeſted in Fleſh; the Holy Ghoſt is God, manifeſting or revealing the manifeſted: thus the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, are not three perſons, but one intire Being, made out in ſeverall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions.</p>
               <p>And thus I have done with this ſubject concerning God, being willing to looſe my ſelf in the thoughts of him, as knowing, that he cannot be known; and that all words, or expreſſions of Scripture or man come ſhort of Him, and do but confound and darken the glory of that great Creator; who hath done all things according to reaſon, and is himſelf the reaſon and ground of all things; for in him they live, and move, and have their Being; and therefore to Him be the Glory for evermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:171557:15"/>
               <head>Concerning Heaven.</head>
               <p>NOw for that which we call Heaven, I cannot conceive it any locall place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God is not confined, or hath his Being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtation in our ſetled compaſſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſee that true which the Letter ſpeakes, <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven is within you:</hi> and ſo I ſee Heaven to be there, where God diſplaies his own glory and excellency; For Heaven is nothing but God at large, or God making out himſelf in Spirit and Glory. And ſo I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſee, that then men are in Heaven, or Heaven in men, when God appeares in his glorious and pure manifeſtations of himſelf, in Love and Grace, in Peace and reſt in the Spirit; when God ſhewes himſelf to be all the happineſs, comfort and reward, and ſo this Heaven is not outward, or a place of any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or carnall bodily happines as men dream of; but it conſiſts in righteouſneſs, joy &amp; peace in the Holy Ghoſt; all which are ſpirituall and terminated in God alone. I do not, as I have carnally conceived, that when <hi>Paul</hi> was rapt up into the third Heaven, and heard and ſaw things unutterable, that he was bodily taken up, or heard God with an audible voice; No, but I rather conceive it ſome extraordinary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171557:15"/>appearance of God, filling the Spirit with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious amazements and admirations of its own excellency. So that, when God doth gloriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare to the ſilencing of fleſh, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering the ſelfiſh Being in man, and fils the ſpirit with its own glory, then is God and his Heaven come in the ſpirit, and ſuch an eſtate ſome may be &amp; have bin ſenſible of, that they have ſo felt the over-powering of God in their ſpirits, that they could not tell whether they were in the body, or out of the body: as was <hi>Pauls</hi> condition.</p>
               <p>And this Heaven the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was a lively Type of, wherein God after he had by a ſtrong hand, brought the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the bondage of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and through many dangers of the Wilderneſſe and red Sea, God at laſt brought them to a Land of reſt, in which this is really made out to me; that it is the over-ruling power of God in us, that takes us from the <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage of ſelf and fleſh, and through the Wilderneſſe and Sea; much toyling and toſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up and downe in ſelfe-Workes and hard duties, outward and carnall ſervices; the Law ſtill beating us to Workes of prayer, humiliation; making us to make Brick with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Straw, and ſetting hard and cruell Task-maſters over us.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:171557:16"/>
               <p> ſo that we may ſay, through many tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we muſt enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but when Gods power is deſtroying theſe enemies of our Peace, and brings us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Land of reſt, that ſpirituall <hi>Canaan,</hi> which we ſpeak of, then do we ceaſe from theſe labours. But truly, this I ſpeake from experience, ſo long as men are under <hi>Moſes,</hi> they cannot enjoy neither muſt they come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Land.</p>
               <p>And therefore, I do not wonder that the Scripture ſpeaks, <hi>Many ſhall ſeek to enter and not be able: and ſtraight and rarrow is the gate, and few there be that finde it.</hi> I would not ſpeak to diſcourage any; but I really appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the greateſt pretenders to Heaven ſcarce know what it is, or will ever enjoy it; but ſhall with <hi>Moſes</hi> onely ſee it a farre off, God not being willing to do any great workes in their ſpirits: becauſe of their unbelief; but what happyneſs and comfort they do enjoy, to whom God appeares thus ſpiritually in, none know but themſelves. This is that heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſpoken of in the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> into which the ſouls of juſt men made perfect are come into.</p>
               <p>The text doth not ſay, we ſhall come to it hereafter; but that we are come unto it, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171557:16"/>that we have full and actuall poſſeſſion of it, and ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Our converſation is in Heaven,</hi> which is nothing but the glorious appearance of God in our ſpirits, when of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall we are made ſpirituall: we ſhall ſee the Scripture ſpeaks of no other Heaven but what is ſpirituall, and not conſiſting of any corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or bodily felicity, as men conceive God, being all the glory and happineſs of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and ſo he that believeth hath everlaſting life within him, and abiding in him; becauſe God there gloriouſly makes out himſelf to be the Life and happineſs. To look for a carnall and ſenſible enjoyment of God, diſtinct from that pure and divine Being of God, ſavours to me of a carnall ſpirit; becauſe it ſets up ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beſide God, when there is nothing that lives and is glorious to all eternity, but God. For as I ſaid before, there is nothing in the creature capable of God, or to enjoy his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor nothing is of God, but is God: becauſe God cannot be devided, nor none can ſhare with him in his Glory, he having not given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny glory to any creature out of himſelf; but what ever the creature apprehends to be its own glory, it is truly and ſpiritually no other but Gods one Being and glory.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:171557:17"/>
               <p> But the truth is, as men fancy a high God though yet very carnally: ſo they fancy a high place for him above the Starrs, I know not where; &amp; herein indeed God condeſcends to the weakneſſe of men in the Scripture, to ſet himſelf and his glorious preſence out to us, as if they were properly in one place more then another, when as we know, a Spirit is not any where confined, but the God of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits is in all and through you all. And ſo Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is his Throne &amp; the Earth his Foot-ſtool; That is, God is in low and dark appearances, as well as in the moſt glorious: God is the high and lofty one that inhabits eternity, and not any circumſcribed place, and ſo he is in low Spirits.</p>
               <p>And the truth is, where God is higheſt in the Spirit, he is ſo low in that Spirit, that they do not deſire any glory out of himſelf; but are willing to be nothing that he may be all. It is very true that the Scripture ſaith, <hi>We looke for new Heaven, and new Earth wherein dwells Righteouſneſſe.</hi> And truly, I find that where God dwells, and is come, and hath taken men up, and wrapt them up into the Spirit; there is a new Heaven and a new Earth, &amp; all the Heaven I look ever to enjoy is to have my earthly and dark apprehenſions of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171557:17"/>God to ceaſe, and to live no other life then what Chriſt ſpiritually lives in me.</p>
               <p>The Scripture ſpeakes likewiſe of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and a City, and Mantions, and that Chriſt went to prepare a place for the Saints, all which are true in the Spirit; For when God raigns in the Spirit, he brings all into ſubjection under him, and ſo he is King and Kingdom himſelf; and Chriſt went to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and to make out himſelf in Spirit, and ſo he left the fleſh to live in the Spirit, and his ſpirituall coming, was much more glorious then his carnall and viſible preſence with them. And the truth is, the one was but a predarative, and fore-runner of the other; ſo it ſo it is ſpiritually true, that he that was leaſt in the kingdom of Heaven was greater then <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt;</hi> where note that thoſe carnall and outward obſervations of Baptiſme, and other adminiſtrations that <hi>John</hi> was in, they were but the preparatives &amp; fore-runners of a more ſpirituall condition, the Kingdom of Heaven not conſiſting in them. And therefore it was reaſoned, <hi>Why do the Diſciples of</hi> John <hi>Faſt and Pray, Luke</hi> 9. <hi>and thy Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Faſt not?</hi> and Chriſt gives them the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:171557:18"/>
               <p> It was his preſence, which is not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of his carnall preſence with them; but of his ſpirituall preſence, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to appear in them; and therefore the Baptiſme of the Holy Ghoſt and fire, was the ſubſtance of which the water Baptiſme was but a ſhadow; and ſo he that was leaſt in the ſpiritual Kingdom, and had a ſpiritual enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him, was greater then he that was the greateſt, and moſt ſtricteſt in the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the outward Duties and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that <hi>John</hi> was under; ſo that it is plain to me, that the ſpiritual preſence of Chriſt, or God in the ſpirit, is the Kingdom of Heaven, into which whomſoever is entered, he ceaſes from the outward and formal uſe of outward Adminiſtrations and Ordinances, and to ſits down ſpiritually in the Kingdom of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and is as the Apoſtle ſaith, allready ſet down in the heavenly places; and when God thus ſpiritually appears in you, then you will be content with me, to ſit down and enter with me into an eternall nothingneſs, and be willing to let God advance himſelf, glorifie himſelf unto all eternity, and ſo caſt down your Crownes at his feet, in everlaſting ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: Into which condition when you are brought, you ſhall not need to expect any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171557:18"/>Heaven; for then ſhall you enter into that reſt wherein you ſhall ceaſe from that labour and toile of outward and formall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: as ſeeing God to be that in you, which you expected in ſelf.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall ſay theſe things are true, but theſe conditions and this eſtate is reſerved for another life: We cannot expect to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect here while we are in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, that it is true we ſhall not; that is, there is nothing of us that is capable of this ſpirituall enjoyment, and therefore we muſt know that our perfection lies not in any thing that the Creature is, but it lies in God, and in that reſpect, unleſs you will ſay God is not ſo perfect here as he will be; we are as perfect as ever we ſhall be, ſo that though this ſpirituall condition be not of us, yet it is in us, and what Heaven or Eſtate God will be in, when he ceaſes to live in the fleſh, I think is as vain for us to imagine, as impoſſible to apprehend.</p>
               <p>Yet if any man can tell me how he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there was a World, I ſhall with as much eaſe tell him how he will be when the World ceaſes to be, and however men are ſo carnal, &amp; women like, that they dream of a Heaven, wherein they ſhall ſit one at the Right hand
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171557:19"/>of God and another at the left, and hope to have much outward felicity and glory, when they have glorified bodies, as they imagine; yet for my part I look for no ſuch condition, and I ſee nothing in the Scripture to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then me in ſuch a conceit.</p>
               <p>For however, it ſpeakes of a City that hath twelve gates and ſtreetes paved with Gold, and yet I ſuppoſe all do but point out the glorious condition that God will appear in upon Earth; and therefore I mind that there was a <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that it is ſaid came down from God out of Heaven: In which there was no Temple, nor needed any Sun or Moon; which as I apprehend, was but that there ſhould be ſuch glorious and ſpiritual diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations and diſcoveries of God in the Saints; and that they ſhould enjoy ſuch a life as that they ſhould not worſhip in any outward ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal way or forme. And ſhould not need to be taught by men or meanes, or of any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Adminiſtrations or Ordinances; But that the Lord God and the Lamb ſhould be their light, and they ſhould be immediatly taught by him; and therefore it is ſaid there was no Temple in it, the Lord and the Lamb, being the light, glory, Temple and all: which condition is glorious, and cannot but be Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171557:19"/>to him that doth enjoy it, and into which I know ſome are brought, and have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the accompliſhment of all thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Propheſies which are ſpoken of in Scripture, and have received that new name, which none know but they that have it.</p>
               <p>And thus have I ſhewed you Heaven, as it appeares in my ſpirit, and for my part I ſee no otherwiſe of it, however men judge, I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to let fall any carnall apprehenſion of a viſible or corporeal enjoyment of God, or any expectation of a happy condition out of God after this life and dayes are ended, being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to reſigne and give up to God what he is in me in fleſh, that ſo God may be all, and advanced above all in the ſpirit. And for my part, I ſee the Lord ſo framing my ſpirit, that I am content to be nothing, that he may be all, though I muſt confeſs, when I think ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly of it, there is nothing ſo grievous to fleſh and blood in me, as to think that all the glory and happineſs that I expected to have had in a corporal and ſenſible enjoyment muſt be terminated in God onely.</p>
               <p>This I am ſure of, that if there be any ſuch thing, I ſhall have my ſhare among the reſt, which for the preſent I think ridiculous to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171557:20"/>looke for; onely this, I wait what the Lord will do in my ſpirit for the preſent. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſweetly refreſhed in the ſpirituall Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of himſelf in me, which is to me <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Angels.</head>
               <p>FOr the Angels I ſee the world as much miſtaken in them as in the former, for I really ſee that man lives in the Angelicall nature, and that the Angels are alſo Spirituall and in man, and herein man is honoured in that God, tooke humane nature and not the Angelicall. For had he confined his own glory in himſelf, he had miſſed one of his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of magnifying himſelf, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he took the humane nature, and ſo was God manifeſt in fleſh, as well as ſeen of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; and as the divine nature is in man, ſo is the Angelicall; and as the one acts, ſo doth the other; for may we not ſee the Angels of God aſcending and diſcending in man? Are not the motions of mans ſpirit here and there in a moment? cannot man aſcend into the hights, and diſcend into the depths? Are not the motions of a mans ſpirit at one end of the World at one time, and at another end of it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171557:20"/>inſtantly again? Doth not God make his Angels ſpirits, and his Miniſters a flame of fire. Is not every ſpirit of illumination? and ſpirituall diſcovery of God? an Angell of God to convey ſome light and influence to the Creature whence is it, that all thoſe ſweet and ſpiritual aſſiſtances and conſolations are flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſpirit; but by the power and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of theſe Angels? It is ſaid the Devill left Chriſt, and Angels came and miniſtred to him, and comforted him. In which I really ſee, every ſpirituall ſupport and comfortable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of God, is an Angel of God. How do the Angels pitch their Tents about them that fear the Lord? which is no other, but that all providences and paſſages watch about them, and adminiſter comfort unto them. I do not as I have conceived, that they are created ſpirituall ſubſtances diſtinct from God, and waiting upon God, as ſerving men about their Lord, to ſee what his pleaſure is; and yet this I know, all accidents that are good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, croſſe or pleaſing, are of God, and are his Angels, and do his will. Theſe are the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels on which God rides in triumph, by which he plagues the World and doth great things in Heaven and Earth; and therefore I looke upon every glorious manifeſtation of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171557:21"/>power and wiſdom of God to be an Angell, when I read of Gods coming with thouſands of his Angels. It refreſhes my ſpirit to think that there will be times of more pure and ſpirituall glory manifeſted. Now there is here and there an Angel or ſpiritual diſcovery of God; then will the world be full of his glory, and all fleſh ſhall ſee the ſalvation of God, I cannot conceive they have any fleſhly forme or ſhape, though it is ſaid, <hi>Lot</hi> received two Angels which is ſpiritually true, for there was ſomething more then ordinary, of Gods mind diſcovered to him: And when I read of the Angel of the Lord ſmiting the Campe of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> that there fell ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in one night; I do not believe there was any viſible appearance, but that there was an extraordinary appearance of Gods power which is called an Angell. And ſo whereever we read of Angels appearing to this or that Servant of God, I cannot look upon them otherwiſe then ſome more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous appearance or manifeſtation of God, and his will and pleaſure concerning things or perſons. And whereas the Scripture ſpeaks of good and bad Angels, I ſee onely this in them, that the one is pure diſcovery of God, the other the more impure &amp; dark; for where as man had a glorious enjoyment of God, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171557:21"/>lived in Gods light, when he left that &amp; went to live in a ſelf-being out of God; There were Angels, Hell, and his diſcoveries of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came dark and confuſed, and ſo brought him into bondage; ſo that the dark and carnall knowing of God is the evill Angel, and the glorious and pure manifeſtation of God is the good Angel: So likewiſe the providences that fall out in the world, that tend to the comfort or well-being of Creatures, they are the good Angels, &amp; the croſſe providences &amp; occurrences that do afflict and grieve a people or perſon, they are the evill Angells or Angels of wrath and diſpleaſure, not that they are ſo indeed, but becauſe the Creature doth miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the mind of God in them; for all things, whether Angels good or evill, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, powers, life or death, things preſent, or to come, are for good to them that are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God. When I read of <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels, and the <hi>Dragon</hi> and his Angels, figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt one another; I ſee nothing there but the fleſhly and dark apprehenſions of God againſt the pure and ſpirituall: and as <hi>Michael</hi> overcame the <hi>Dragon;</hi> ſo the more pure and ſpiritual diſpenſations of God ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power the dark and carnall, and ſo thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of darkneſs ſhall be caſt into their lake, and there be reſerved to the great judgement
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171557:22"/>day of the Lord within us, when he ſhall ſit as a refiner in our ſpirits, then ſhall the chaffe be burnt up &amp; conſumed by the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and fire of theſe Angelical appearances of God; &amp; this was an Angel of God comforting me againſt all the aſperſions of hereſie &amp; blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, that the people of God lye under at this day; and ſo you ſee what I thinke of the Angels, and what they are.</p>
               <p>And thus have I done with that which I call <hi>The light ſide of God.</hi> I come now to the dark, and ſhall begin with that firſt which is called Devill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Devill.</head>
               <p>I See; that which we call the Devill is alſo in man; and yet I cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend him to be a creature, as men generally do; For then I muſt give him a Being, and there is nothing hath a Being but God; (that is formally and properly) yet as men ſpeake, though improperly, there is ſuch a thing as we call Devill; which I conceive to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the fleſhly Being; or, as men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſpeak, the corruption of nature; or, as the Scripture calls it, <hi>the old Man,</hi> and this alſo moves, and acts in all thoſe things which we call ſinfull. So that ſo far as a man lives in a ſinfull being, ſo farre the Devill
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171557:22"/>in him; and therefore when <hi>Mary Magdelen</hi> had 7 Devils caſt out of her, it gives me to conceive that every ſin is a Devill and ſo far as a man is led aſide of his own luſts, ſo far he is led by the Devill; and therefore he is called Satan, Tempter and Deceiver, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other expreſſions. And hence it is, that whatſoever is hatefull or hurtfull to man, we uſe to ſay, the Devill is in it: and ſo every thing that doth hinder or darken our ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all comfort and peace, that is a Devill in us. God is Light, and in him there is no darkneſs; and it is as true, the Devill is darkneſſe, and in him there is no light at all: And ſo farre as yny man is in that darkneſſe, ſo farre he is in the Devill, ſo much the nearer he comes to him: and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>You are of your Father the Devill, and his workes you do:</hi> God is the Way, Truth, and Life, and the Devill is falſehood, his wayes tend to darkneſſe and end in death and deſtruction. This is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciever that would perſwade us of a happyneſs of our own, and a glory out of God; He is that Myſtery of iniquity, that man of ſinne whom the Lord is continually deſtroying, and for whoſe deſtruction God is man'd in our fleſh, and as the Devill the deciever hath led us from God to live a life of our own: ſo God
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171557:23"/>in us is reducing us againe to live in himſelf, and ſo the ſpirituall ſeed is breaking the head and power of the carnall; this Devill is the ſpirit of envy, malice, cruelty, ever ſeeking to devoure and rob us of that which is moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to us. Men fear a Devill without them, and ſo fancy him to be terrible in their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, never conſidering that he is in them; and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>The Devill entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Judas,</hi> not but that he was in him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but then was there a more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary appearance of him, and ſo he is that <hi>Judas</hi> indeed, which is ever betraying the ſpirituall Chriſt into the hands of ſelf and fleſh, and is continually crucifying the Lord of life, and putting him to open ſhame, and vailing his glory under ſhadowes, making men to take them for ſubſtances, and ſo is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming himſelf into an Angell of light: and ſo makes men put light for darkneſſe, and darkneſſe for light: exalting himſelf, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading ſelf and fleſh to have high thoughts of himſelf: and ſeeking to put out all that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall light and glory, wherever it appeares in the ſpirits of men. So that, however men aſcribe a Being and perſon, a Him to him; yet there is nothing ſo, neither would I call him any thing, but as it is the language of men to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171557:23"/>expreſſe our ſelves to one another about that which wee call Devill.</p>
               <p>And ſo I ſhall leave the Devill, and ſpeak ſomething of Sinne: becauſe that is moſt like him, being of the neareſt Kindred to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Sinne.</head>
               <p>FOr Sin, I cannot tell how to call it any thing, becauſe it is nothing; I cannot give it a name, becauſe it is no ſubſtance or crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; It is rather Primitive then Poſitive, we call it and give it a Being, though indeed in it ſelf it hath none It is no act, for then it were viſible; but Sin is inward and ſpirituall, as that is which we call Grace and Holineſſe; it is therefore called ſpirituall wickedneſſe, it is rather the defect of Grace and a deficiency in the Creature, then any act as viſible to the outward view.</p>
               <p>Further, Sin as Sin admits of no degrees for that which we call a great ſinne, is no more then that which we call the leaſt; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would not be thought to leſſen it while we ſpeake of it, we ſhall give you our thoughts of it in the language of Scripture;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171557:24"/>And therefore we ſee, the Apoſtle deſcribes it to our hands, where he ſaith, <hi>We have all ſinned, and are deprived of the Glory of God.</hi> So hence I conclude, that ſinne is a coming ſhort, or a deprivation of the Glory of God; and ſo farre as a man is ſhort of that glory, or doth not live and act in that divine Being: ſo farre he ſins, ſo farre as he is in darkneſſe, and hath this glory vailed in him: ſo far he is ſinfull</p>
               <p>In brief, ſin is a living out of the will of God; for God being the Supream will, and having ordered all things and perſons to be in ſuch and ſuch a condition; this ſelf and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Being wills ſomething of its own below Gods Will, and ſo prevaricates from that, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in his own will; and ſo ſins. Hence it is, that Nations and perticular perſons, are grieved and diſcontented with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayes &amp; times a part, as if they could alter the Supreme Will; not conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Supreme will muſt be ſubjected unto, and that they muſt receive evill from the hands of God as well as good; and not knowing, that all is in the ordering of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme will, and ſo run to this and that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and formall duty, and ſo are carnall and ſinfull while they think they do God good
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171557:24"/>ſervice, and yet I do not condemn them in ſo doing; for to them it is their light, though they be truely and ſpiritually in darkneſs; and though men act in darkneſſe, yet God is there vailing his glory, and ſo they muſt needs ſin; for ſin is properly the dark ſide of God which is a meere privation of light.</p>
               <p>Further, we muſt conſider, that God gives not any Law or Rule out of himſelfe, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his own glory: And as himſelf and his own glory are the ultimate end of all actions, and the ground of them; and as they are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall &amp; inward: ſo thoſe ſpirituall and inward acts or motions that fall below, or tend to the croſſing of this deſign of God, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull: and yet, in ſome reſpect theſe alſo tend to the glory of God, and ſin it ſelf doth as well fall in compliance with the glory of God, as well as that which we call grace and goodneſſe; for <hi>ſinne abounds that grace may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound much more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And however men ſpeak of offending God by ſin, and the Scripture ſpeaks of provoking God to wrath by the ſins of a people; yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to me it is apparent, that God is no more provoked by ſin to wrath, then he is allured to bleſſing by any holineſs of a people or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: And therefore <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lords</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:171557:25"/>hand is not ſhortned, that he cannot ſave, or his eares heavy that he cannot heare; but it is their ſins that hide his face from them: In which I really ſee, that it is not as men gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally take it, that ſin cauſes God actually to withdraw himſelf, or to alter his porpoſe of good to the Creature; but the truth lies in this, that there is that people are as near and ready to be helpt and ſaved of God when they ſin as when they do good. But onely this there is, that in the nature of ſin, that guilt and condemnation to it, &amp; that accuſing power it is of in the Conſcience, that men miſ-apprehend and do miſconceive the face or countenance of God to them, and ſin it is, that is that vaile or covering over the face &amp; glory of God, that hinders the ſhining of it in the ſpirit. For the Sun doth ſhine as clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when the Cloudes interpoſe betwixt us and it, as when it is a clear day, onely it doth not ſo appear to us: and ſo it is with God, the ſin is the Cloud that interpoſes betwixt God and us, though God be the ſame and all one to us when we ſin, yet we do not ſo ſee it, ſo that it is not a peoples ſinning or doing good that is any cauſe in God, of good or evill to the Creature; for what abſurdity would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low if God ſhould hide his face, and let out
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171557:25"/>his love upon the Creatures ſinning, or doing that which we call good: how mutable ſhould we make God to be, whereas we know that all accidents and occurrences are the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtations of that ſupream Will and Power which is immutable and unalterable, whether the Creature ſin or do well.</p>
               <p>And whereas ſome may ſay, then men may live as they liſt, becauſe God is the ſame, and all tends to his glory, if we ſin, or if we do well:</p>
               <p>I anſwer them in the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: Men ſhould not ſin becauſe grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds; but yet if they do ſin, that ſhall turn to the prayſe of God, as well as when they do wel. And ſo the wrath of man praiſes God as well as his love and meekneſs, and God glorified in the one as well as the other. And however this may ſeeme to countenance that God is the Authour of ſin, and wills ſin; yet to me it is plain, that there is nothing that hath a Being but God, and ſin being a nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, God cannot be the Author of it, and ſo falles not within the decree of God; for ſo far as God was in man, and made him, ſo far he is God; but it was the man, the ſelf-being that found out many Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And all things that God made were
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171557:26"/>very good when he lookt upon them; But ſinne God could not behold, becauſe it was not.</p>
               <p>Herein is God glorified in ſinne, as contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſet together illuſtrate one another: and God is glorious and powerful in the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that fleſhly Being, which is exalting it ſelf againſt the divine. And therefore is God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in our fleſh to deſtroy the workes of fleſh in us; and he is plucking down thoſe principalities and powers, and deſtroying that old man with his deceiveable luſts, and form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the new man which is himſelf, or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Being, and new man in us.</p>
               <p>Further, I ſee that the reaſon why we cal ſome men wicked and ſome godly, is not any thing in the men; but as the divine Being appeares more gloriouſly in one then in another: ſo we ſay, the one is a Saint and godly, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is wicked and profane; and yet the one acts as he is carried forth by the Supreme power, and ſo doth the other: And if there be any difference it is not in reſpect of the creature, of what it is, or doth; for the ſame divine Being, is in the one as well as the other; but onely it doth not ſo manifeſt it ſelf in the one as the other. And therefore, as I dare call no man good becauſe there is none good but
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171557:26"/>God: ſo I dare call no man wicked or ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe it is God only that makes the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and who am I to judge another mans Servant?</p>
               <p>And I ſee alſo that the ſame power that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables a man to do good, the ſame power pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents a man from evill. For neither the evill act or the good act are evill or good, as they are acts; and men can no more do evill then they can do good, as they call it: which may anſwer that common Objection that men make.</p>
               <p>That if this be ſo, men may drink, ſwear, and be profane, and live as they liſt.</p>
               <p>And I anſwer further, the ſin lies not in theſe outward acts, for a man may do the ſelf-ſame act, and yet not ſin: that is, that a man drinks to exceſs, there is the ſin, that a man drinks for neceſſity or delight; the ſame act and poſture of body is put out in the one, as the other: And ſo I might inſtance in the reſt, ſo that the ſin is from within: The luſt within, and an inward luſting after the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, beyond that end for which God hath deſigned it.</p>
               <p>And further, this I affirm, that a man as man hath no more power or freedom of will to do evill then he hath to do good. I think
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171557:27"/>
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> had as many opportunities to commit folly as any man could have; and yet ſaith he, <hi>How can I do this and ſinne againſt God?</hi> So that it was the power within which kept him, though queſtionleſſe, he might have had a naturall inclination to have done the act as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men.</p>
               <p>And I believe <hi>Eſau</hi> had as much will and power as a man, to do his brother <hi>Jacob</hi> a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and to take away his life; but when God once appeared to him, then inſtead of killing him he imbraces him &amp; ſo might be inſtance in divers other examples. So that, hence I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, it is onely the powerfull preſence of God in one man more then another, that one man acts not as vilely as another.</p>
               <p>Again I apprehend further, that there is not two wills in God, as men generally teach and affirm; that is to ſay, an active will and a permiſſive will, and ſo a power to make a man to do good, and another kind of power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine a man from evill, and ſo men confound the power and will of God, when as indeed: they are not diſtinct in God; for Gods power and will are all one: his will is his power, and his power is his will: and by the ſelf ſame act that he wills things, by the ſelfe ſame act he doth things, and it is our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171557:27"/>otherwiſe to apprehend; for God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one and intire, admitting of no diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or diviſion in himſelf, he admits of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riations, but all things are as that ſupreme will acts, and brings them forth; And I ſee according to the Councell of his will, they did no more that crucified Chriſt, then they that did imbrace him.</p>
               <p>Theſe things I write, not to countenance any unſeemly act or evill in any man; And I know, God being purity it ſelf, cannot behold uncleanneſſe, and his Spirit in me doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it wherever I ſee it, and I cannot but reprove it where ever it is found; Neither can I ſo cloſe in ſociety or fellowſhip with thoſe that are in darkneſs, or walk unbeſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly not becoming the Goſpel; and yet I know, that if the grace of God appeared in them, it would as well teach them, to deny un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe and worldly luſts: as to live righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and ſoberly in the World: Onely, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to open the nature of that which we call ſin, and to make it as ſpiritually vile as I can: For I ſee my ſelf to have been miſtaken, and I ſee others are in ſin, as well as in that we call grace &amp; goodnes; For as I have made the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall and outward performance of a Duty, the onely thing wherein grace and godlineſs did conſiſt ſo: have I made the outward doing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:171557:28"/>or not doing of an act to be the ſin; But I really ſee, that neither the one or the other, as an act is either good or evill: But as godlineſs is a myſtery and inward, and is within us: ſo is ſin likewiſe a myſtery and alſo within us; and therefore it is called, a myſtery of iniquity, from whence proceeds murders, adulteries, and are they not from the luſt within? The inward luſt and acting, is the ſin which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary or below God; the outward acting or putting forth of that inward luſt, is the ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt man, and is below a man: and whether the thing or ſinne be acted outwardly, or no, there is ſin; And therefore, the ſpirituality of the Goſpel is above the Letter, the Letter onely forbiding the outward act of adultery, but the ſpirituality forbids the very luſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and therefore, he that looks on a woman with a ſecret and inward luſt, hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſin in the Spirit and heart: as if he had done the outward act, and is in Gods account an adulterer: And all the uſe I can make of the premiſſes, duely conſidered, it rather aggravates the nature of ſin, then extinuates or leſſens it; for I can ſeriouſly reflect upon my own ſpirit, and ſee more ſin within, then all the world can do without; I ſee that I have framed and fancied a God without me, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:171557:28"/>have given him an outward Worſhip while I have ſeem'd to be very ſpirituall, and ſo have been very far from that ſpirituall worſhip of him which is like himſelf, and conſiſts onely in Spirit and Truth; for what a vaine thing is it to me for a man to put off his Hat, or kneele and ſhow an outward reverence to an inviſible God: and how carnall have I been, and men are in ſetting dayes and times a part to expreſſe an outward humiliation for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and ſpirituall ſacrifice, whereas there is no humility but in the Spirit; and there is no ſpirituall exaltation of God; but when the Creature ceaſes from being, or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing, and makes God All; whereas men think to get pardon and peace from God by a ſelf-humiliation, prayers and duties, and I know not what: and ſo give that to a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and a prayer, which is the onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per worke of God, who ſubdues our ſinnes, and pardons them for his own Names ſake.</p>
               <p>And ſo I have done with that which we call ſinne, which we call a privation of God, or the living below God; you ſee we have made it ſomething and nothing, in reſpect of God it is nothing; for he knowes no defect, neither is he in darkneſſe; but is all glory and light.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:171557:29"/>
               <p> Again, it is ſomething in reſpect of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; becauſe it is in darkneſſe and lives not in the light and glory of that God; and there is that in the Creature, which as a vaile covers and hides the glory of God, and ſo it is ſinfull: and yet here is God in all this; for ſhould the Creature ſhare in the Deity, God would not be ſo glorious; and ſhould the Deity par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Humanity, and be one with it, there would be no ſin, and therefore is God manifeſt in fleſh, but not to fleſh; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the Divine Nature and Being live in the Humane, but is not the Humane, nor is the Humane capable of any conjunction or union with the Divine; and therefore the Divine lives in it ſelf, and the Humane or fleſhly Being lives in it ſelf; and as the fleſhly Being is below the Divine: ſo men living in it are ſinfull; and as that acts: ſo they act ſin, which is all at preſent I ſee of that we call Sinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Hell.</head>
               <p>HAving ſpoken of the Devill and Sin, Hell muſt needes follow; for no ſooner did
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171557:29"/>Man leave to live in the Divine Being, and ſo lived in himſelf; but he was turned out of <hi>Paradiſe</hi> to digg for his living, and to worke, labour and toyle, to maintaine a ſelf-Being, and to procure a ſelf-happineſſe, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he came to ſhame and miſery; he eating of the forbidden fruite, which was his own holineſſe, righteouſneſſe, all is curſed to him, and ſo the man is in Hell: ſo that our ceaſing to live in God, and living in the ſelf-Being, is the Hell; For that Angelicall life in us, being vailed and covered, we live in the Diabolicall; whence it is we are in Hell. As ſoone as man ceaſt to live in the light, but he would be knowing ſomething, and doing ſomething: ſo ſoone did he fall into a <hi>Chaos,</hi> and all was darkneſſe: and ſo that develiſh and ſelf nature is in man, and he is reſerved in chaines of darkneſſe till the judgement of the great day of Gods appearing in his Spirit, and till then he is in Hell, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till God Judge and burne up that fleſh, and carnall knowing of him; and reduce him to his firſt Being, to live in God till then, he ſuffers the fire of Hel in himſelf ſo that the Hell in a mans ſelfe and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation is, that a man is condemned of himſelf.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:171557:30"/>
               <p> What adoe there is in the world to find Hell where it is, how many have puzled and beat their braines to find it out, as if it were a locall place? and therefore ſome becauſe they would make it contrary to Heaven and as they fancie that the higheſt place, ſo they will be ſure to make Hell the loweſt, and therefore being as carnall in the one as the other, make it to be the loweſt part of the Earth. Others, becauſe they find a place ſpeaking of the Devill, calling him the Prince of the Aire, they will make Hell in the Ayre I know not where. But as the Devill rules onely in Aierie and light ſpirits ſo I look upon this to be a Aierie fancy: For as the Devill is, and hath his Throne and Seat in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man, ſo is his Hell; &amp; truly for my part I think they cannot be ſeparated, and therefore I conceive any man that is in bondage to his own luſt; nay further he that is under the Law or in any formal or outward duty, &amp; is ſo poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with a ſpirit of bondage, that he muſt be ſo and ſo, do ſo and ſo, or elſe he muſt be damned, and in the doing of ſuch and ſuch things he ſhall be ſaved: this man is in Hell, and Hell in him, and needes no other Devill to torment him, but his own falſe and carnall apprehenſion of God; for as the ſpirituall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:171557:30"/>of God doth neceſſarily and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally make Heaven, and cauſe joy and peace in the ſpirit: So the dark and carnall conceit or knowledge of God muſt needes cauſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and lamentation, and makes Hell.</p>
               <p>I do not much wonder at the carnall Papiſt, no more then at the carnall Proteſtant, the one fancying a carnall purgatory, the other a carnall Hell.</p>
               <p>And I think the one gets as much money for frighting men with the one, and making them believe they can ſhow them the way to avoid it, and bring them to Heaven, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth in frighting them with purgatory, and making the poor people believe they can keep them from that. But I let that paſſe.</p>
               <p>And however, the Scripture ſpeaks of Hell, and expreſſes it by fire and brimſtone, and the worme dying not, and many other expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It ſpeakes as in other caſes, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men, not that there is ſuch viſible and material formes of puniſhment: But that as fire and brimſtone are the moſt fearful things to the nature of man; ſo doth the Scripture ſet out the miſerable and fearfull Eſtate of a carnall condition, and what miſeries and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments do accompany ſuch an Eſtate. And what conſequences have followed the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171557:31"/>man from being in ſuch darkneſs, and what the abſence of God hath cauſed in the ſpirit, the Scriptures and many daily examples do abundantly teſtifie: whoſe terrors and diſtractions in their ſpirits have been ſuch as have been eaſeleſs and remedileſs, and made them willing to become their own Butchers, and all this hath been from a miſapprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and confuſed knowledge of God. The truth is, I ſhall ſpeak from my own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſo long as I was in bondage, to dayes, times, and ſet times, that I muſt pray ſo often, and do ſo much, frequent ſuch Ordinances, ſo long I was in trouble and ſorrow; for I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſaw there was this and that failing, and miſcarriage in every duty that I ſuffered tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my ſpirit, for fear I ſhould never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain my end, which was a carnall and ſenſible enjoyment of ſome happineſs which I called Heaven, and when I was inlarged in this and that duty, I thought then all was well, and that I ſhould go to Heaven: And ſo I was continually ſuffering the torment of Hell, and toſſed up and down, being condemned of my ſelf. And this is all the condemnation that I ſee is come into the World, that men love darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:171557:31"/>are evill, That men live in love, the dark and fleſhly Being, and not in the light, in the divine being; this is the condemnation not cauſally but formally: And this is that I found til God appeared ſpiritually, and ſhewed me that he was all the glory and happineſs himſelf, and that fleſh was nothing, and ſhould enjoy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and then I could not but ceaſe from my former fleſhly actings which cauſed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but fear and trouble, and ſaw God, or rather God made out himſelf in me joy and peace, and brought me into the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Sons of God, whereas I was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in bondage to ſin, law, an accuſing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which is Hell. And yet I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude God in all this, for if we deſcend into Hell he is there: He is in the dark, though we ſee it not as well as in the light that we ſee: He is in wrath and ſeverity, and we are wiſht to behold him in both; let there be never ſuch confuſions of ſpirit, never ſuch terrors and Hell, let there be darkneſs and no light: yet there God is, there is ſome glimps of himſelf, in as much as there is a ſecret go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the ſpirit towards God, and all the diſtractions the Creature lies under, is becauſe it cannot enjoy the preſence &amp; love of God, &amp; yet God is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171557:32"/>there amidſt all that darkneſs and raignes in the midſt of his enemies, and ſo he deſcends into Hell, and returnes with a glorious try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, riſing with abundance of joy and peace in the ſpirit: So that though the Earth be moved, and the great mountains which the Creature had made to it ſelf, be tumbled up and down, and the Creature have no reſt, but is eaſeleſs and reſtleſs, yet God is there as a Rock unſhaken of any ſtorme, but is ſweetly refreſhing and delighting himſelf with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo enters into the ſtrong mans houſe, and diſarmes him, and bindes him hand and foote, and caſts him into utter darkneſs.</p>
               <p>And to ſumme up all, if there be any that think this is not Hell enough to be inwardly and ſpiritually tormented. Let them but conſult with thoſe that have been under ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall deſertions as they are called, and have cryed out as if their bones had been broken, and would have choſen death rather then life, and thought they could have indured many burnings to have been rid of ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
               <p>And I think they will tell them there is no other or need be no other Hell, and all this comes from a dark and carnall knowledg, or rather ignorance of God, for certain it is, God
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171557:32"/>condemns none. But the condemnation is of a mans ſelf, and in a mans ſelf.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall ſay, all this is nothing; I care not, if this be all the Hell, and that it laſts no longer then this life; But is there not a Hell hereafter, that is, the Hell to think of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and that the Creat re ſhall be everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly tormented, and indure the wrath of God to all Eternity?</p>
               <p>For anſwer hereunto, I muſt profeſſe, I do not know of any ſuch thing, nor do I conceive what ſhould be thus tormented; for that which men call a ſoule, I had thought to have made it a particular of the preſent diſcourſe; but I ſhall referr it to further conſideration, onely to ſtay any mans appetite that deſires my opinion of it, I ſhall onely give him this morſell to chew upon, and that is this:</p>
               <p>I do wonder how any man can make it to be capable of any torment, when as it is well known, it came immediately from God, and is no other but of God, and if I may ſay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without offence, it is God; for that which is of God is God, becauſe God cannot be divided. All men grant it is immortall, and came from God pure and undefiled: And how then it ſhould be impure, I know not;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171557:33"/>for this I really ſee, that though it was infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into the body, yet I am ſure it was not of the body, nor could the fleſh be capable of ſuch a thing as we call union with the ſpirit, and ſo the ſoule is in the body; but is not of the body or the body, but really diſtinct; and ſo it is in fleſh but not fleſh, and ſo it is God manifeſt in fleſh: But not in union or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with fleſh, but hath a diſtinct and formall difference, both here and hereafter, the one returning to nothing, the other living to all Eternity.</p>
               <p>And further, how this ſoule, as men ſpeak of, ſhould be impure and ſinfull, I know not; for how fleſh ſhould defile a ſpirit I cannot I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine, being that I am ſure, and as every man will grant, That no effect can be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced beyond its cauſe; but every effect hath its riſe and originall from its proper cauſe: And ſo hath God laid in nature the body proper to the ſeed, and to every ſeed its own body. And a man may as well gather Grapes of Thornes, and Figs of Thiſtles, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, it can be that a viſible or fleſhly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance can corrupt a ſpirituall and inviſible ſubſtance: But then you will ſay, where is the ſin all this while? you will ſay then, ſin is nothing, or that there is no ſin. To which I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171557:33"/>have partly anſwered in the foregoing Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſpoken of, which becauſe it is ſo faln in my way, I ſhall ſpeak a little further in anſwer to you.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I ſhall grant, and I think it is no leſſe then blaſphemy to affirm otherwiſe, that God is not the Authour of ſin, or that any ſin can be in him, he being light, and in him is no darkneſs at all, and ſo the ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, it muſt needes be pure and holy, not admitting any mixture of fleſh, or that which we call corrupted nature. And yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine</p>
               <p>Secondly, I cannot conceive there ſhould be ſin, untill God was pleaſed to let out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in fleſh: But for before he lived in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo there could be no ſin, there being nothing but God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Inaſmuch as this fleſh is a vaile or covering, wherein this ſoule or divine Being lives: this God, ſoule, or divine nature, (call it what you will) the glory and beauty, the purity and excellency thereof being darkened and obſcured, there is the ſin: For whatever men conceive of things, this I really appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, That that which we call the ſoule, that is as men generally make it.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:171557:34"/>
               <p> The underſtanding, reaſon, judgement, will, and affections are not poſitively or actually infected with ſin; but onely are obſcured, and cannot be ſo gloriouſly manifeſted, by reaſon of the fleſh or fleſhly Being: and ſo God tooke fleſh upon him, and through the vaile that is the fleſh, did deſtroy, and doth condemn ſin in the fleſh: So that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prays or propheſies with a vaile or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring upon his head: Chriſt which is God in the Spirit, ſuch a one diſhonoureth his head, which is Chriſt, becauſe he ſuffers, ſomething to come betwixt God and him. So that by this time, I ſuppoſe you ſee what I conceive of ſin, and where it lies, and what I conceive of that we call ſoul, and of the body or fleſhly part of man, wherein I have been forced to make a little digreſſion, becauſe things are myſterious.</p>
               <p>And to come to the point in hand, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Hell hereafter, what it ſhould be, or what ſhould be tormented in it, I do not as yet apprehend; for the ſoul came pure, and is of the eſſence of God, could not be corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the body not capable of any impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God, and returns to its firſt principle, of earth: ſo that unleſſe you will imagine a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171557:34"/>Hell in God, which you would account Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy to ſpeak: I cannot fancy or imagine any ſuch Hell hereafter as men dreame off.</p>
               <p>The truth is, there is nothing lives to all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity but God: every thing below God periſheth and comes to nothing: and as all things had their ſubſiſtance and Being in God, before they were ever manifeſted in the world or Creatures: ſo in the end, whatſoever is of God, or God in the world at the end of it, they ſhall all be rapt up into God againe. And ſo as God from all eternity lived in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and all things in him: ſo when he ſhall ceaſe to live in fleſh and creatures, he will then live in himſelf unto all eternity, and will glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly triumph over Sin, Hell and death; and all Creatures ſhall give up their Power and Glory unto God backe againe, from whence it Originally came, and ſo God ſhall be All.</p>
               <p>However, if any man can imagine, that there will be any dark appearance of God hereafter, or unto all eternity, then may he conclude a Hell; for as ſin is the dark appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God: ſo is Hell an inſeperable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of it; but to imagine the one or the other hereafter, or to all eternity, would
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171557:35"/>render me in my owne apprehenſion one of thoſe whoſe property it is to believe every thing; but I know whom I have believed.</p>
               <p>Thus have I done with that part of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which I call the dark ſide of God, which I divide into three parts which we call <hi>Devill, Sin,</hi> and <hi>Hell:</hi> In all which I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to clear God, and to make the Devill and ſin as vile as I can; but am far ſhort of the one or the other, wanting words to expreſs my ſelf in either, onely what was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my ſpirit thou haſt in the Letter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Reſurrection.</head>
               <p>NOw let us come to deliver our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that which we call Reſurrection, and to expreſs it as it is in me. I ſee it alſo to be ſpirituall and inward, and is alſo of that which is the inward man: For though I know the inward man which is God or the divine Being, admits of no degrees, either is more or leſſe; but yet in as much as this God is more gloriouſly manifeſted at one time more then another in man.</p>
               <p>Hence it is that we give this Title of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:171557:35"/>of the Creature after this life is ended? But truly, for my part, I am fully ſatisfied in my own ſpirit with thoſe words of Chriſt, where he ſaith, <hi>I am the Reſurrection and the life:</hi> and I ſee it fully made out in me, that Chriſt ſpiritually is that reſurrection, which I thought ſhould be of the creature. And I cannot tell what in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould riſe or be capable of ſuch glory and happineſſe beſide God, and ſo I ſee that which I did expect to enjoy hereafter onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and peculiar to God, for I really ſee that after God is manifeſt in fleſh, and ſeen of Angels, preached in the world, and believed in, that then he ſhall after all this be received up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to glory, and that fleſh and bloud cannot inherit the Kingdome of God: and that nothing lives to all eternity, but pure Divine glory. I cannot conceive any other reſurrection then of carnall to be made ſpirituall, and that is no other then the ſpirituall appearance of God: ſo that when I would find out what the reſurrection is, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon my own ſpirit, and trace the goings of God there, and there I can find God riſing from one degree of glory to another, and changing me into his image by his ſpirit: and ſo I ſee how he hath led me from one diſpenſation to another, and from one ordinance to another, till at laſt he appears ſo ſpiritually that he over-powers all fleſh and formes which I admired in my carnall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:171557:36"/>and appears to be that temple, glory and light himſelfe, which I had thought to have had in a ſenſible and carnall enjoyment hereafter, ſo that I am led to believe that there is no ſuch out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward felicity to be enjoyed in this reſurrection: but that it is God ariſing in the ſpirit, and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning brighter and brighter, till the perfect day: &amp; making all the creature-apprehenſions, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God to ceaſe, and this reſurrection I clearly finde in my owne ſpirit, that the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and inlarged parts and abilities in prayer, ſpeaking, or otherwiſe, in which I have delighted, and no queſtion but I did enjoy God in them, though in a darke and low eſtate: theſe I ſay, the glory and beauty of them are all withered and vaniſhed before the bright and glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of God in the ſpirit; for the Son in me having delivered up his Kingdome, and thoſe fleſhly and formall manifeſtations, and outward bodily worſhips ceaſing, God is all in all, ſo that I can neither in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or in the Mount, or in any outward form or duty worſhip God, knowing that he is only to be worſhipped in ſpirit &amp; truth, and that though God was with me in my former carnall and dark condition, and did lead me in it gently, yet all was but to raiſe up himſelfe, and to be that ſpiritually in me in another way then that which I expected, and ſo of naturall he hath made me ſpirituall, which is the ſpirituall reſurrection that we are ſpeaking of.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171557:36"/>And further I really ſee that the fleſh of man, and of all other creatures differ not any thing in the nature of them indeed, in reſpect of the kind and manner, ſome fleſh is of men, ſome of Beaſts, and ſome of fiſhes: but as fleſh none of them are capable of any more glory then one another, all being of the ſame mould, and comming to the ſame end, and though the ſpirit in them, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is God in them, return to their originall, which is God, and ſo lives in him again, yet the fleſhly part returns to duſt from whence it came: and as the man dies, ſo dies the beaſt; as dies the wiſe man ſo dies the foole, one end is to them all as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks: and whereas men imagine that there is a fleſhly reſurrection, and that the ſame body fleſh and bones ſhall riſe and remain a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and viſible ſubſtance: how this ſhould be I am ſure they do not know themſelves: for however men ſpeak that the corporall body ſhall be made a ſpirituall, to me it is ridiculous, becauſe the Scripture ſaith, <hi>That which is borne of fleſh is fleſh,</hi> and can remaine in no other capacity. And beſides, I hope no man will deny, that a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall thing can be ſeen of a fleſhly, or that an externall organ of the body can ſee an internall and inviſible thing, the Apoſtle makes it plaine, that the things which are ſeen are temporall, and the things that are not ſeen are eternall. Now how it can ſtand or conſiſt with reaſon or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171557:37"/>Logick or Rhetorick, that men ſhould hold and maintaine that men ſhould viſibly ſee one another in heaven as they call it, and know one another, and ſee their viſible ſhape as they lived in on the earth, &amp; yet they maintaine on the other ſide this is a ſpirituall body: I cannot ſee if this be divinity, then I am not in the humanity; but indeed I am willing to give way to their weakneſſe, becauſe I have been as childiſh my ſelfe, only I cannot but take notice of the <hi>Babell</hi> and confuſion that men are in, and yet thinke themſelves the only Embaſſadours of peace, and as if all knowledge and ſpirituall learning were confined to them, but laying my hand gently on their ſore, I let them paſſe, and go on to that in hand.</p>
               <p>And whereas the Scripture ſpeaks of a ſpirituall body, I conceived that there is a ſpirituall body, and that this body muſt be raiſed: which ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all body I apprehend to be nothing but the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Being, or God in ſpirit: termed a Body for theſe two reaſons as I conceive: Firſt, becauſe God is the body and ſubſtance of all things, and ſo it is ſaid, that this God dwelt bodily or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially in the man Chriſt, he being that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in whoſe fleſh God did more gloriouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear then in any other, ſo he was the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Image o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Fathers perſon, and in this reſpect God may be termed a ſpirituall Body,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:171557:37"/>though for my part I dare not imagine him to have either perſon or body. Secondly, God may be ſtiled a ſpirituall body; becauſe this body or divine Being is, and hath its Being in many Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. And ſo God is ſtiled the head of the body, and Chriſt is the head of the Church, which is his body, wherein Ireally apprehend that all the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of God in the Saints as they are called, &amp; all the manifeſtation of God in fleſh, or in any fleſhly or outward diſpenſation or form; they are but the Carkes and ſhadow of God who is the body or ſubſtance of them all, and all theſe dying and vaniſhing as they ſhall: God ſhall onely live and raiſe himſelf a ſpiritual body, and therein live to all eternity; ſo that it is ſpiritually true, that the body which is fleſhly ſhall periſh, and the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all body ſhall be raiſed, as we ſhall have occaſion in the ſequel of the diſcourſe to make out; but becauſe men are ſtill poring upon a Scripture without them to prove a carnall Reſurrection, and will believe nothing but what they think the Scripture ſpeaks in the letter, though indeed they erre, not knowing it or the power of God: I ſhall a little condeſcend to their weakneſs in this kind: though for my part, if there were not a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in all the Bible to ſtrengthen me in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Reſurrection I ſhould not much care, nor need I the teſtimony of it as to my ſelf; for I have a ſurer word within, to which I take heed: yet I ſay for other mens ſakes, I ſhall take the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171557:38"/>moſt principall places of Scripture that men look upon, which ſpeak of the Reſurrection, and in the ſpiritual diſcoveries of them; if there be any thing to ſtrengthen them in their opinion, I ſhall and muſt give way.</p>
               <p>And we ſhall begin with that which is the prime piller of their Faith, and that is in the 1. of the <hi>Corinths</hi> 15. from the beginning to the end of it. It being the whole ſubject of the diſcourſe therein to treat of the Reſurrection: The drift of the Apoſtle is to prove the ſpiritual Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt to be as ſure and certain as his fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and by the ſame Argument that he proves the one, by the ſame he alſo proves the other, in a ſpiritual ſenſe. And the compariſon lies not betwixt the fleſhly riſing of Chriſt, and the fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly riſing of men, as moſt men imagine; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the fleſhly riſing of Chriſt in the humanity, and his ſpiritual riſing in the divinity, and ſo all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, you ſhall ſee the compariſon holds betwixt the naturall and the ſpirituall, and not betwixt the naturall and the naturall. And that we may ſee plainly it appears in the 47. verſe, <hi>The firſt man is of the Earth earthly; the ſecond man is from Heaven who is the Lord:</hi> ſo that we ſee, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the outward earthly man, and the Lord from Heaven which is the ſpiritual, and ſhewes evidently, that it is not the earthly man that is raiſed, but the ſpirituall, and ſo Chriſt after the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:171557:38"/>fleſh was but of the earthly man, and ſo muſt be deſtroyed and ſubdued, as wel as other things and formes, which did accompany that earthly being, and as the one vaniſhed out of ſight before the Apoſtles; ſo muſt the other, and that this may not ſeeme ſtrange to any man, that the fleſh of Chriſt muſt be deſtroyed, as well as other things. It is plain in the 28. verſe.</p>
               <p>So that it is apparent, that the Sonne of man being of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> after the fleſh, muſt as well be ſubdued and periſh with the fleſhly forms and adminiſtrations that did accompany him: For certain I am, that as he was God or the divine being in him, he could not be ſubdued, ſo that it is very clear, that it was the fleſhly appearance that muſt needes come to nothing as well as the fleſhly forme in other Creatures; and ſo Chriſt did ceaſe to live in the fleſh, that he might more tranſcendently live in the ſpirit, and ſo he laid down his humanity to live in the Divinity: and ſo it is true what the Apoſtle ſaith in the 20. <hi>v.</hi> That as Chriſt is riſen from the dead, and is become the firſt fruits of them that ſleep and are dead in him, ſo ſuch as are dead in him ſhall ſurely riſe. That is, they ſhall as ſurely riſe to a ſpirituall condition as they have been ſpiritually dead in him. And ſo he goes on in the 22. verſe. As in <hi>Adam</hi> all dyed, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive: Here is ſtill the compariſon betwixt the natural and the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:171557:39"/>ſpirituall: that is, as ſure as the fleſhly <hi>Adam,</hi> and outward viſible forme dies, ſo it is as certain, they that are in Chriſt or the ſpititual man, ſhall be made alive and quickened, and God ſhall riſe and appear in more power and glory in that life of the ſpirit then ever he did in the fleſhly forme or ſhape. But to go on, The firſt fruits is Chriſt, and then they that are Chriſts at his coming: which is thus, that as Chriſt herein was the firſt fruits of them that did live in the ſpirit; as he ſaith, a little while, and you ſhall ſee me, and a little while, and you ſhall not ſee me, becauſe I go to the Father: that is, he was to lay down the fleſh to live in the divine and ſpiritual life, in which he appeared after his aſcenſion, and ſo was as good as his word, and did come in ſpirit; ſo it ſhould be as ſpiritually true, that they ſhould partake of the ſame ſpiritual life, and live in the ſame ſpiritual Reſurrection as he, and live in the Father as he did; and therefore he comforted them, and told them, I aſcend to my Father and your Father, to my God and your God: But yet in the mean time, till the Son of man and all fleſhly formes were ſubdued to the Father, till men were brought to live in the Father, and to live in a ſpiritual life: till then Chriſt muſt raigne, till then there muſt be outward formes of Chriſts death, and there muſt be manifeſtations of God
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:171557:39"/>in fleſh, and outward Ordinances. But when theſe are ſubdued, then men muſt riſe, or rather God will appear to be that ſpiritually which they before enjoyed, onely in an outward manner as is argued by the Apoſtle in the 25. verſe: And the laſt enemy is death: And certain it is, this death muſt be deſtroyed; and the dead muſt riſe, or elſe death cannot be deſtroyed:</p>
               <p>Now this muſt needes be a little opened, that ſo we may ſee what the Reſurrection is; for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, the dead muſt ariſe, or elſe Chriſt cannot be riſen.</p>
               <p>For the opening of which death we ſhall take the ſame method as the Apoſtle doth here, to compare the natural with the ſpiritual Then we ſay a man is dead, when a man is void of all viſible ſence and motion, when he ceaſes to act or move, when the life is departed, when the life is departed, when the being ceaſes to live in the fleſh, that he cannot move to any outward or naturall act.</p>
               <p>And ſo a man is ſpiritually dead, or dead in Chriſt, when a man ceaſes to be or act any thing in the things of God; but is moved and acted, as God is in him: when there is nothing of the ſelf-being appearing; in a word, when to the world he appeares to act nothing do nothing in an outward and formall way, ſo that men think there is no ſpiritual life in him.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:171557:40"/>
               <p> Then doth he die in the Lord, when he wholly reſignes up all his grace, abilities, knowledge of God into God, and knowes not what he doth, or is or ſhould know ceaſing from his own reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings forth after God, living and being to any ſelf-enjoyment, or expectation of any future felicity, life or comfort out of God: For it is certain ſo long as the Creature thinks that he muſt act or do ſomething to attain ſalvation, or be any thing diſtinct from God, ſo long he is alive without Gods life, and ſo muſt needes be miſerable, and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, if in this life our hope was, we were moſt miſerable: which life is not to be underſtood of the fleſhly Being: But in this life that is, if our happineſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts did depend upon our owne ſelf-actings, and on our own being any thing, were we moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p>But our hope is, that all our felicity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is terminated and centred in God onely. And ſo Chriſt ſpiritually in us is the hope of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is a myſtery; and ſo being dead in Chriſt, when Chriſt riſes, we ſhall be ſure to riſe with him: ſo that there is a ſweet truth in that Scripture, where it is ſaid, That the day of a mans death is better then the day that a man is borne: For better it is for a man to die ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, then to live naturally.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:171557:40"/>
               <p> And ſo none of us liveth to himſelf, or dyes to himſelf; but whether we live or dye, all is in the Lord: and he is glorified in the death, as well as in the life: for our life is hid with God in Chriſt, as the Apoſtle ſaith to the <hi>Colloſſians:</hi> though we be dead as he ſaith, and nothing appeares of life to our ſelves or others, yet we need not fear; for the life is hid with God in Chriſt: And when Chriſt our life ſhall appear: and ſo appear as to be our life and happineſſe, then ſhall we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear glorious, but it is in him; when Chriſt riſes ſo ſpiritually and gloriouſly, to ſubdue and deſtroy the fleſhly being, which is the death and cauſes death; for no ſooner did ſin enter, but death en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with it, then doth Chriſt the ſpirituall being and life triumph. And then is death ſwallowed up of life, and mortality of immortality; That is, fleſh is ſwallowed up of ſpirit, and death the fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being is ſwallowed up of life, the ſpirituall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And then ſhall be brought to paſſe that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, O Death where is thy ſting! O grave where is thy victory! But thanks to God, for it is he that gets the victory: again as it is in the naturall, ſo it is in the ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>This Reſurrection is ſet forth by the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of the graine of Corne, and it holds out a lively reſemblance of the ſpirituall life and death, and of the ſpirituall Reſurrection of the naturall; for as the graine of Corn dyes before it lives, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:171557:41"/>in this death there is life hid: ſo in this ſpirituall death there is ſpirituall life, though it be hid and lye buried in the grave of earthly and carnall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions: as God gives the one a Body, and is himſelf the ſubſtance and Body, and the life: ſo doth the ſpirituall Body, the inward and ſpirituall life which is God, riſe to more glory then ever he did appear in in the earthly and outward forme; and as the fleſhly appearance dyes and ceaſes, and as in the death there is life: ſo God when he ceaſes to live in fleſh, he lives and riſes with much more glory in the Spirit: And yet it is true, till the fleſhly and outward form or formall Being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Divine cannot reigne; and therefore in the midſt of death there is life, and God doth but dye in weakneſſe to riſe in power: Not that God is weak, but he is buried and hid in the carnall ſenſe and life, to riſe with more ſtrong and glorious appearances of himſelf, which is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Reſurrection; which is further illuſtrated, by the terreſtriall Bodies, and the heavenly Bodies which doth but further confirm the ſpirituall ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Chriſt; For though there be a glory in the tereſtriall and outward diſpenſations and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtations of God in them, ſo when God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to uncloath himſelf, and to let out himſelf in pure and heavenly diſpenſations, when theſe come and appear, and that God puts on the heavenly clothing, then is the corruptible ſwalled up of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:171557:41"/>incorruptible; For it is true, that fleſh and blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God, nor corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion put on incorruption: but when there ſhall be a change, and of naturall we become ſpirituall: and when the laſt Trump ſhall blow, that is, when God ſhall gloriouſly ſound forth his one praiſe &amp; nothing but ſpirituall power appears; Then ſhall the dead hear the voice of the Sonne of God and live, and the dark and carnall appearances of God ſhall give way to the more pure and ſpirituall; and then ſhall God gloriouſly triumph over Sin, Death and Hell, and live without any vaile, in his own pure and divine glory. The conſideration of which is ſufficient, to perſwade me to be ſtedfaſt and to abound in the work of the Lord; knowing that though my labour be in vaine, as to ſelf, or fleſh, yet it is not in vaine in the Lord: he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the end and ſumme of all.</p>
               <p>Thus have I as briefly and plainly as I could gone over the ſubſtance of the whole Chapter, though much more might be ſpoken; being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to my own ſpirit, that I have not hid or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed any clauſe, which might ſerve to ſpeak for a carnall Reſurrection: or for a riſing of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy after its diſſolution here in any viſible form or ſhape; But that as the light is in me: ſo have I manifeſted it out to others; and do onely referre my ſelf for tryall, to that light which manifeſts all things, leaving other men to their own darke
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:171557:42"/>and carnall apprehenſions of a carnall Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and conclude, that the Reſurrection is from the carnall to the fleſhly Chriſt: from Chriſt living in the fleſh, to his living in the Spirit, which is that I call the Reſurrection; and if time and mens pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience would ſuffer, I could eaſily prove, that whatſoever Chriſt as man was, or did from his Birth to his aſcenſion, in his life and death in the fleſh; they were but all Types and ſhadowes of what he would be, and work in his glorious coming in the Spirit, and ſo they are applyed all along, if men wil let the Scripture ſpeak in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Letter; but I let it paſſe at preſent.</p>
               <p>And further, to gratifie mens weakneſs, I ſhall proceed to another Scripture, which is as carnal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly urged as the former, to prove a carnall Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; and that is in <hi>Matthew,</hi> concerning Chriſts reaſoning with the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> they denying the Reſurrection: And Chriſt proving it to them, by ſaying, That he was the God of the living and not of the dead: and ſo, that though <hi>Abraham, Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were dead long agoe; yet they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: But to open this Scripture, we muſt know what Reſurrection the <hi>Sadduces</hi> denyed, and what Reſurrection Chriſt proved; I affirm, that it was the ſpiritual Reſurrection which they denyed and that appeares plainly, by that in the 23 of <hi>Acts</hi> 8. where it is ſaid, that the <hi>Sadduces</hi> deny the Reſurrection or Angell or Spirit; but there is no mention of the Reſurrection of the Body.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:171557:42"/>And ſo it is clear, that Chriſts argument to them was to prove a ſpirituall Reſurrection, and ſo it holds a full proof of what we affirme, and a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll anſwer to the <hi>Sadduces;</hi> For God is not the God of the dead, but of the living: not of fleſh, but of Spirit: And ſo <hi>Abraham, Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> they did really and ſpiritually live in God, though they were dead in the fleſh; So that I conceive, and it is clear to me, that a ſpirituall and Angelical appearance of God, is that Reſurrection which is held forth and which ſhould be; and they are the <hi>Sadduces</hi> that deny this ſpirituall Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Another Scripture which is alledged to as little purpoſe, is that in <hi>Iob</hi> 19. I know my Redeemer lives, and that I ſhall ſee him with theſe eyes; I do wonder, what a God men fancy to be ſeen with a fleſhly eye: I alwayes took God to be a Spirit &amp; inviſible, and that no created fleſhly things was able to ſee him. I cannot imagine then how <hi>Jobs</hi> eyes, which were and ſhould be in a viſible form and ſhape, ſhould be capable of ſuch a Divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible viſion: But yet if <hi>Job</hi> was ſo carnall to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that his fleſhly eyes ſhould ſee a ſpirituall God: yet I am not.</p>
               <p>And if any man ſhall ſay, that Chriſt hath a Body in heaven which he lived in when he was upon the earth: and that may be ſeen being vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and corporall; for that when any man ſhall prove heaven a locall place, and that God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:171557:43"/>ſits there, and receives petitions from his Son Chriſt, as men do viſibly here on earth: then I ſhall give him an anſwer, neither have I ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſt to make him to conſiſt of fleſh and bloud, or bodily ſhape in heaven (as men call it) for though it be ſaid, that <hi>Steven</hi> ſaw the heaven opened, and Chriſt ſitting at the right hand of God, yet am I not ſo carnall to believe, That <hi>Stevens</hi> fleſhly eyes might ſee up above the ſtars, and skies, and that the houſe top might be open where he was, and ſo he bodily ſaw Chriſt ſitting in a bodily ſhape at the right hand of God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. As a Diuine of <hi>Leiceſterſhire</hi> did affirm to me, in a private conference that he thought it might be ſo. But his divinity being as little as his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I leave him, as knowing that the man Chriſt left his fleſhly being to live in the divine, which is void of all forme and ſhape, or to be ſeen viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly by any outward or corporeall ſubſtance, and that no light can ſee him, but his own, and when men live in this light, then they will agree with me, till then, I muſt leave men to their dark and carnall apprehenſions, In the meane time I am content to be nothing that God may be all, and to let fall my thoughts of any glory or excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hereafter, as a creature; as knowing that the fleſhly man dies, that the ſpirituall may be raiſed, and that all creature or ſenſible enjoyment of God ſhall ceaſe in eternall ſilence: and it is fruit
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:171557:43"/>and joy enough in my ſpirit, that God hath ſo diſcovered himſelf in me that I can willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve all my comforts, joy and peace into God, who is that endleſſe and infinite Ocean, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſire to be comprehended of it, then to comprehend it: ſo that by all that hath bin al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, I cannot ſee that there is any thing in that called Scripture to prove any fleſhly living of the body after this life, but that all things and Creatures below God periſh and die, and God onely lives, and riſes in more power, and glorious appearance then ever be was in when he lived in the fleſh: which is that reſurrection which is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and which we have endeavoured to make out, and ſo I leave it, and come to the laſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of my diſcourſe, which is that we call <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> and becauſe men are as carnall about that as any of the former, and becauſe the ground of all the miſtakes in the former is onely the miſ-appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the Scripture we ſhal inſiſt upon that a little the more larger, and ſo conclude.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Scripture.</head>
               <p>IF you take Scripture as it was written by the Prophets and Apoſtles: It is a forme of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome words, a perfect rule, for all outward acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a true Guide for a mans outward converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among men: The livelieſt expreſſion of the mind of God, of all other books; ſetting forth all conditions, eſtates and enjoyments of all men in the world, it is the word in fleſh, <hi>The word was made fleſh,</hi> it is the higheſt diſcovery of God in fleſh,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:171557:44"/>the trueſt teſtimony of God in the world: I do verily believe, that what pitch ſoever any man hath or can attain unto, but it is able to ſpeak to him in it thus, it is in the letter, and the out-ſide of it.</p>
               <p>But if you ask me what I make Scripture? I look upon it to be ſpiritual, and ſo it is the Law written in the heart, and ſo it is ſpirit and life, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The words that I ſpeak are ſpirit and life:</hi> ſo that what Chriſt ſpeaks ſpiritually, that is Scripture, and ſo it is the power of God; for take Scripture as it is in the Hiſtory, it hath no more power in the inward man, then any other writings of good men, nor is it in that ſenſe a diſcerner of the ſecrets, as it is in the Hiſtory, ſo it is to be believed above all other writings in the world; but as it is a myſtery, and God being the ſubſtance of it, ſo I muſt believe it as God makes it out in me: I muſt not build my Faith upon it, or any ſaying of it, becauſe ſuch and ſuch men writ or ſpeak ſo and ſo, But from that divine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation in my own ſpirit; for the Scripture, as it is written outwardly, is but an outward wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that which is within; and the ſpirituality of it wherein the life and being of it doth conſiſt, is made out by a ſpiritual diſcovery. I do not go to the letter of Scripture, to know the mind of God; but I having the mind of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I am able to ſee it witneſſed, and made out in the Letter; for if I do a thing lawfull
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:171557:44"/>from the Letter; yet if I be perſwaded in my own ſpirit I ſhould not do it, I ſinne. Yea further, that power and authority which the Scripture hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, is not becauſe ſuch and ſuch men writ it; but from that divine manifeſtation in them: And ſo indeed, if I have the ſame diſcovery that they had; then I can ſay, it is the word of God, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I lie; for it is one thing to believe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe ſuch and ſuch write it, as moſt men do: and it is another thing to believe it becauſe God ſaith ſo in me; and ſo it is the ſpirituall ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God that is the Scripture, and ſo that is true. They that are of God hear Gods Word: Now no man can hear God, but as God ſpeaks: And it is as true, that as God ſpeaks ſpiritually: ſo no man hears him but in a ſpirituall manner, and ſo we hear Gods word. And therefore it is ſaid often in the 1. <hi>Rev. He that hath an eare, let him hear what the ſpirit ſaith to the Churches;</hi> Which cannot be underſtood of a carnall eare, becauſe every man hath that; but as the Spirit ſpeaks ſpiritually: ſo it is the ſpirituall eare that hears the Spirit: For all the outward ſpeaking or hearing of men or Scripture, cannot reach the Spirit. Further, the Scripture I do apprehend, as it is written outwardly, is God clothed in fleſhly tearmes and expreſſions, and ſpeaks in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of men, as when he ſpeaks of himſelf; and he uſes ſuch expreſſions as are higheſt in mens eſteem, and his commands, threatnings and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:171557:45"/>admonitions, exhortations, they are all as men ſpeak to one another; for I dare not believe God is this or that, or can be named by any title, or that he ever threatned any people or Nation; or promiſed any, that upon ſuch and ſuch terms they ſhould have this or that, or upon neglect of him they ſhould ſuffer this or that; for to me it plainly appears, that there is neither wrath or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, love or hatred in God, or that God was any thing more or leſſe to a people, upon their ſinning or doing any good; For then a thouſand abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties would follow. But the truth is, becauſe men apprehend anger when they ſin, and God pleaſed when they do well; therefore men ſpeak as one to another, and God ſo far condeſcends, as to ſpeak to men in their own language; But that he is ſo in himſelfe, I ſhould think blaſphemy to affirme; for I am confident there is never an error or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in the world as men maintaine; but if men take that for Scripture, which they call the Bible, it doth fully and literally countenance and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold: and I know no other way in the world, to uphold the authority of Scripture, than to make it ſpirituall. And whereas men ſpeak that we deny Scripture: I muſt confeſſe for my part, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I know no greater door opened to the denying it, then for men to preſſe, and urge men to do ſuch and ſuch things, becauſe the outward word ſaith ſo and ſo: indeed, ſo far I ſhall deny it as the Letter is inferiour to the Spirit: ſo far I conceive,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:171557:45"/>the letter doth vaile and ſhadow the ſpirituality of it. And if men have the Law in their hearts, and be taught of God, they need not run ſo often to a great Bible, to relieve themſelves in ſtraights and doubts as men generally do, never reflecting upon their ſpirits, to ſee what God ſpeaks there; I do not ſpeak it to condemn the practiſe, neither is the fault in the Book, but in mens carnall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of it; and ſeeing men make an Idoll of it, and think the reading and peruſing the outward word, is enough to cure all their wounds, and to reſolve their doubts; ſo that as men look upon God outwardly and carnally: ſo do they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to an outward word, to ſtrengthen their carnall apprehenſions. Truly, I muſt confeſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly, that as to my own ſpiritual enjoyment, I ſee nothing of any concernment in it, or in look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon it, but onely this I ſee, and ſo it is ſome comfort to me to read, that God hath diſcovered himſelf in others as well as in me, and that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſpeaks the ſame in me, as it did in them. But for any thing of God that I look to attaine unto by reading or looking upon it, I do not care whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever I look upon one again or no: And yet this is no detracting from the glory or authority of Scripture; becauſe the Scripture is within and ſpirituall, and the Law being writ in my ſpirit, I care not much for beholding it in the Letter; but as to the ends aforeſaid. And the truth is, it is the Law in the ſpirit that is the true Bible, the other
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:171557:46"/>is but a ſhadow or counterpart of it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do not expect to be taught by Bibles, or Books, but by God: nay further, I do not do any thing, or abſtain from any thing, becauſe the outward letter commands or forbids it: but by reaſon of that commanding power which is God in me, and his ſpeaking is the power of God to ſalvation, and it is in that by which I live, and by which I act: and ſo the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the law outward, that it was not made for the righteous, but for whoremongers, and ſuch and ſuch.</p>
               <p>And ſo I ſee, that if men were acted &amp; guided by that inward law of righteouſneſſe within, there need be no laws of men, to compel or reſtrain men, and I could wiſh that ſuch a ſpirit of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe would appear, that men did not act or do things from externall rules, but from an internall law within: Again to ſpeak a little further, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Scripture, men generally ſpeak, that we muſt do nothing but what we have a rule for, and are asking, what warrant have you to do ſuch a thing? ſhew a rule from Scripture, and then we will believe you, or elſe it is but a whimſey, and I know not what; Truly, it is true, and I would thoſe that talk moſt of a rule, did ſee that rule; for the ſafeſt and prime rule that I know for any man, is that pure ſpirituall law and rule of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is within, and ſo far as any man doth any thing beneath or beyond that, ſo far he doth
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:171557:46"/>that which he hath no warrant for: but who muſt judge of this rule, whether this or that be according to the mind of God or no? To this I anſwer, in the words of Scripture, becauſe men will ſooneſt believe me: That it is the ſpirit which ſearches all things, even the deep things of God: and there is no knowing the ſpirit but in its own light which is ſpiritual, &amp; therefore I think it not ſo ſafe to go to the Bible to ſee what others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpoken and writ of the mind of God, as to ſee what God ſpeaks within me, and to follow the ducture and leading of it in me, I ſhall ſooner, and ſo others ſhall ſooner, miſ-apprehend the mind of God in other men, then in my ſelf, and the ſame law and rule being in me which was in thoſe that writ the Bible, and to which internall and ſpiritual rule within, I muſt take a meaſure and ſcantling of all my actions, I had rather mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them from or by a rule within, then by any outward rule or word whatſoever; for the one, that is to ſay, the Bible without, is but a ſhadow of that Bible which is within, which is the Law ſpiritual, the ſafeſt and onely rule.</p>
               <p>If any man ſhall ſay, that I may be deceived, and take that for a diſcovery of God which is but a fancie of my own Brain: I anſwer, I may miſ-interpret the outward Scripture, and ſo run as great a hazard that way, and as ſoon fall into errour, becauſe it ſpeakes of and to men in varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Eſtates and conditions, and ſo if I take that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:171557:47"/>part of it, which doth not ſpeak to my condition, I ſhall then make a falſe conſtruction of it, ſo that I conceive the fareſt and ſureſt rule to walk by, is that law of the ſpirit, and as many as walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſpirituall rule, peace ſhall be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and on the <hi>Iſrael</hi> which is of God; but as many as walk according to a rule without them and ſo look for a God and Scripture without, they ſhall be but at a loſſe, and live in continuall trouble and diſquietment: and if I may ſpeak my own experience without offence, ſo long as I li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and looked upon the outward ſcripture, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward commands and duties, ſet times of humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, prayer, &amp; I know not what, I was always toſt to and fro like the waves of the ſea. But when God appeared and ſhewed me that there was no ſcripure God commands worſhips, but what were ſpirituall like himſelfe, and within men, and what he was the authour and end of, and that all things elſe were but ſhadowes; what ſweer, peace and comfort, I then did, and do now enjoy, I might tell you if I could; for the truth is they are unſpeakable: and ſo it is the ſpirituall diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of God that is the Scripture I look upon: and if ſo, then I muſt needs inferre, that thoſe in whom Chriſt is ſpiritually diſcovered, and that live in a ſpirituall enjoyment of him, they muſt needs be beſt able to ſpeak the language of the Scripture, and to give the ſenſe and meaning of it, and are beſt acquainted with the originall: for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:171557:47"/>God being the Authour of it, they in whom he is moſt ſpiritually diſcovered muſt needs know the mind of it, and what Scripture is; which may exclude all outward parts of learning, arts, and other qualifications, which men boaſt of; for though they may ſerve to ſpeak ſcripture out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and help to expreſſe men to one another, and to read it in the ſeverall tranſlations of it, from one Nation to another; yet they all come ſhort of the ſpirituall diſcovery of God, and ſo are not eſſential to the knowledge of him; he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely known and ſeen in his own light. And which may likewiſe condemne the <hi>Romane</hi> Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, I think the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Divines may take their part herein; That having attain'd a little skil in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral languages of ſeveral countrys, and received or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination (as they call it) they think themſelves ſo inveſted with power above their brethren, that none muſt be infallible or authentick in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Scripture, but themſelves and men of their order; and unleſſe they will ſay them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that private men (as they call them) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have the ſame, or more ſpirituall diſcovery of God then themſelves, I do wonder that they ſhould ſo advance themſelves, and undervalue or deſpiſe others.</p>
               <p>But we ſhall let them paſſe and return to what we have in hand, and we ſhall ſee both the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and end of Scripture, laid down by the Apoſtle in the 2 of <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. where he ſaith
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:171557:48"/>all Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> profitable to teach, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that the man of God may be made perfect; where we ſee plainly what I have ſpoken all along, That the inſpiration which is ſpiritual and of God, is the true &amp; proper ground why men are taught, and no man can be taught, but it muſt be by a ſpiritual inſpiration, or elſe it is not of God: and ſo the Scripture is not of any private interpretation; but holy men ſpeak as they were inſpired ſo that, that which gives the riſe &amp; ground of Scripture is Gods ſpeaking in men, or inſpiring men, and they beſt know what is Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in whom God moſt powerfully ſpeaks. And it is as true that God ſpeaks ſpiritually in man, and not in any audible voice or forme of words; for I do not conceive he ever ſpoke ſo to any, he being void of all ſhape and form, or bodily Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. And when God ſo ſpeakes that from natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, they are made ſpiritual, then is it indeed they are ſpiritually taught. And to this ſweetly falls in that of <hi>David:</hi> thou haſt taught me truth in the ſecret parts; then indeed men come to be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of their former weak and carnall condition, when God ſpiritually diſcovers himſelf in them: So that it is not the reading or peruſing of the Scripture in the letter of it: for ſo a man may read all his life-time, and be never the better that teaches men ſpiritually: But when the Scripture is ſpiritually made out, and interpreted in them, then they are taught: And then it is,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:171557:48"/>that the man of God is made perfect; then doth the inward fleſhly Being, or carnall man appeare dark and carnall, and the ſpirituall or the man of God, comes to be perfect: and this ſpirituall man is able to judge all things as the Apoſtle ſaith, then can he ſpiritually diſcern the Scripture in him, and ſo can read it true in the outward let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; For I really ſee, that all the knowledge of the Scripture in the letter of it, reaches no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but to a hiſtoricall and fleſhly knowledge of God, and indeed to this kind of knowledge, which many do boaſt of, the Scripture is very helpfull. But he that knows no further then the outward letter, knowes but Chriſt after the fleſh. And though ſo I have known Chriſt, Scripture and God, yet henceforth know I them ſo no more; they being ſpirituall. Again, this I conceive, that all the whole ſtory and letter of the Scripture, doth but ſet out and ſpeak but of two eſtates and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men or in men: that is the fleſhly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and the Divine; the naturall and the ſpirituall man: And all theſe are preſented to us in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral degrees and actings in each ſtate, and perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated in ſeverall perſons from the beginning to the end of the Bible. And ſo <hi>Gain</hi> and <hi>Abel, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael, Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau, David</hi> and <hi>Saul;</hi> and ſo the good Kings and the bad, the good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and the wicked, the true Apoſtles and the falſe; they do but all expreſſe both Eſtates, and are not ſo much to be lookt upon in their ſeverall
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:171557:49"/>perſons; but are really fulfilled and appliable to every man in each Eſtate, Degree, and Condition whatſoever. As to inſtance, it tels us of the Man Chriſt, who lived and died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and that he roſe from the dead, and aſcended and paſt through all conditions: But alas, how farre is this from reaching the ſpirit, a man may read it, and believe it, and yet be never the better, do him no more good then any other Hiſtory which we call prophane. But the ſpirituality and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and that which is ſpirit and life, lies in this to ſee him found in the ſpirit, to die in him, and to riſe with him, to aſcend and ſit down with him in the heavenly places, being made conformable to him in the ſpirit to have the everlaſting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel preacht in the ſpirit. All which the Hiſtory and Perſon of Chriſt and the outward Goſpel, are but ſhadows: the other is the ſealed Book which none can read, till God open himſelf to be the Scripture: Then indeed can we underſtand what Scripture is, and then are we guided by that inward life and ſpirit of truth, more then by the outward letter, and teachings in the World. So that it is not the Hiſtory of Scripture that is the Scripture, or that is the word of God, but it is the ſpiritual ſpeaking of <hi>God,</hi> which is the word of <hi>God,</hi> and is ſpirit &amp; life. But ſome may ſay, doth not the word ſay, Hear and your ſouls ſhall live; and faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God? Is not the Scripture and outward letter
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171557:49"/>a meanes to convey the knowledge of God, and meanes to ger Faith? To which I anſwer, it is true; but what living is it to which hearing is annexed. If an outward and carnall living and knowing of God, then the outward Scripture contributes to it; but if it be a ſpiritual living, which is a living in God, then that life muſt be enjoyed by a ſpirituall hearing: for all the outward hearing in the world cannot reach to that, ſo that to me it is plain, that then men ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally live, when God ſpiritually ſpeakes, and ſo this ſpiritual life is attained by a ſpirituall ſpeaking of God; and when men heare that ſpiritual ſpeaking, then their ſoules live ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually in that, and ſo the word of Chriſt is verefied; That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an lives not by bread onely, but by every word which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes out of the mouth of God, that is, it is not any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or external way or meanes that ſupports the Spirit, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is the divine and ſpiritual food, that the divine and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual man lives upon, and on that he feedes ſpiritually with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſatisfaction: it being ſutable to him; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> onely bleſſed that eat bread in the Kingdom of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: for they never hunger or thirſt after any externall or outward teaching or ſpeaking of men; and ſo it is true, that faith comes by hearing. But what do you make of Faith? If it be a ſpiritual thing, as it is, then it muſt needes come by a ſpiritual meanes, which is a ſpiritual hearing, and ſo the following words explain it, That hearing comes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the word of God: Now it is apparent, that God ſpeakes ſpiritually, and ſo he is heard and believed ſpiritually; and men cannot heare God ſpeak, but it muſt be by a ſpiritual hearing, ſutable to the ſpeaking. But men are ſtill objecting and ſay, did not Chriſt and the Apoſtles convince men of the truth of things by the Scripture, ſhewing things muſt needs be ſo. I anſwer, it is true, but the reaſons plain which was, that becauſe men were not able to bear Chriſts ſpiritual ſpeaking, it being myſticall: therefore he ſpeaks to them in parables, and in ſuch a way as they could apprehend, and ſo did condeſcend to their weakneſſe, and ſo Chriſt ſpeakes of himſelf, that he needed not Iohns Teſtimony, he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſufficient proofe with himſelf, and needed not any mans
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:171557:50"/>Teſtimony of him. And beſides, as men did haſten their lief of things upon an outward letter: therefore Chriſt the Apoſtle brought Scripture to prove things, that he mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> bear them with their own weapons. And ſo alleadged Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the Devill, to anſwer him in his own way. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtles brought Scripture to prove a Chriſt in the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which ſome went about to deny. And whereas ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> alleadge that to the Law and the Teſtimony, if any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeak not according to that, it is becauſe there is no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in him. It is alſo true, if any man ſpeak not from that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tuall Law in himſelf, and hath not the inward Teſtimon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the ſpirit within: in ſuch a man there is no truth, let ſpeak what he will, and this is the grand cauſe why me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> diſpute and jangle about things, becauſe men ſpeak not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the inward experience and ſpiritual teaching, but from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dition and the outward letter. Nay I verily believe mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Religion in the world is borne up, becauſe others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> held and done ſo before them, and they think it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> to walk in an outward conformity, in duties and Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and never eye the goings of God in their own Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> But this by the way, and all I drive at in this, and I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> no body will be offended, that I would make Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is to be ſpiritual, and not ſubject to the groſs and carna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> prehenſions and interpretations of any ſort of men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ever; neither dô I leſſen the Authority of it in ſo doing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the reaſon of all the miſtakes in and about the Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not in the Scripture, but in mens carnall apprehenſions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> For if men were ſpiritual, they might judge it alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpiritual as God himſelf i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And I would have men ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon a ſure foundation, which is God and that Divine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> within us, which is pure and Divine Scripture.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:171557:50"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
